<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some prison meditations and directions on several subjects viz. on [brace] the fall of man, the sufferings of Christ, repentance and faith, reproof and counsel, the holy Scriptures, prayer, love to mankind, sincerity, the vanity of the world, the benefit of affliction, heaven and hell / by Samuel Young, minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Trepidantium Malleus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y88A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42476516</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42476516</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2260:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some prison meditations and directions on several subjects viz. on [brace] the fall of man, the sufferings of Christ, repentance and faith, reproof and counsel, the holy Scriptures, prayer, love to mankind, sincerity, the vanity of the world, the benefit of affliction, heaven and hell / by Samuel Young, minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Trepidantium Malleus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.A. for Tho. Cockril ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151471:1"/>
            <p>SOME PRISON MEDITATIONS AND DIRECTIONS On ſeveral Subjects: <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>On The Fall of Man.</item>
               <item>On The Sufferings of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>On Repentance and Faith.</item>
               <item>On Reproof and Counſel.</item>
               <item>On The Holy Scriptures.</item>
               <item>On Prayer.</item>
               <item>On Love to Mankind.</item>
               <item>On Sincerity.</item>
               <item>On The Vanity of the World.</item>
               <item>On The Benefit of Afflictions.</item>
               <item>On Heaven and Hell.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NG,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 33.1, 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Moreover the word of the Lord came to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> the ſecond time, (while he was yet ſhut up in the Court of the Priſon) ſaying, Call unto me, and I will anſwer thee, and ſhew thee great and mighty things, which thou knoweſt not.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luther</hi>'s Song, <hi>Col. Men.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Credens tribulatur, Tribuſatus invocat, Invocans auditur, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus laudat.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. A.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Cockeril</hi> at the three Leggs in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151471:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151471:2"/>
            <head>To all that are ſerious in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion, whether <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts</hi> or <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or People.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Eternal God having ſpread open the everlaſting arms of Mercy, and embraced you, hath made you ſo like himſelf, as that you have ſuch a hatred to ſin, as ſin, and love to holineſs, as holineſs, that cannot be quenched: Hence it is, that you being ſuch God-like Creatures, are often in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angs, becauſe of a diſtracted world; whoſe Lives are a delectable Frenzy, or a continued fit of madneſs: To you do I call, that being Converted, you would often ſpeak of the chief things in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (ſuch as are contained in this Book) to a vain world, that <hi>Many may be by you turned unto Righteouſneſs:</hi> I foreſee that ſeveral Queſtions will by ſeveral men be made, concerning the Author and the Book: As,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What Opinion is the Author of?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I Anſwer. He is of this Opinion,
<pb facs="tcp:151471:3"/>that to love God with all the heart, and with all the underſtanding, and with all the ſoul, and with all the ſtrength, and to love his neighbour as himſelf, is more than all whole Burnt-offerings and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.33. He diſowneth all thoſe Names which have occaſioned ſo many heats and heart-burnings among us, and wiſheth they were as little known among the Saints on Earth, as they are among the Saints in Heaven. He is an impartial enquirer after Truth, without regard to intereſt or parties; he is of all your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions to whom he writes, and yet of none of them; of all, ſo as to mind the great things you plead for, as Love to God, Chriſt and Souls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> above all; of none, ſo as to be tyed to any of your controverted modes of Diſcipline; he is a mourner over all your parties, that God and one another are no more loved, but a furious Contender for none.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why in the following Meditations and Directions, are Books Quoted, and not Chapter and Page?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe I have been for above two years from my Study: The Obſervations are my own, in the diligent peruſing and reading over all the Authors I have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: And now I call on you that know
<pb facs="tcp:151471:3"/>God, and are known of him, that you love one another: If your heads muſt differ, reſolve that your hearts ſhall unite.</p>
            <p>Are you ſuch as frequent the <hi>Liturgy?</hi> Call on them that worſhip with you, not to mock God, when they profeſs to come before him with <hi>an humble, lowly, penitent and obedient heart;</hi> when they ſay to God, <hi>Pitifully behold the ſorrows of our hearts:</hi> Perſwade them, when they bring their Children to Baptiſm, not to make it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a matter of cuſtome to give the Child a Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chooſe no ignorant or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous <hi>God-fathers</hi> or <hi>God-mothers</hi> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mind their own Souls, and therefore in vain promiſe to mind the Souls of your Children: Remember what a weighty matter it is to give up your Children to the Lord: What cryes ſhould there be at <hi>the throne of Grace,</hi> what pains ſhould you take as they grow up, that they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be his: Thoſe that go with you to the Lords Table, as you have opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, perſwade them, that their words be right, when they ſay, <hi>The thoughts of our ſins are grievous, the burthen of them is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable;</hi> and when they reſign them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to God, to do it unfeignedly.</p>
            <p>You that frequent private Aſſemblies,
<pb facs="tcp:151471:4"/>chiefly or only; <hi>Love them that hate you, Pray for them that are in Authority, let all men by your good Converſations which they ſhall behold, glorifie God in the day of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.12.</p>
            <p>In whatſoever dreſs your Religion is cloathed, whether in a more plain or curious one, <hi>Love one another.</hi> Perhaps a Priſon may, in time, make many of you to fall into one anothers Arms, and weep bitterly for your former Animoſities. Remember <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Hooper!</hi> The ſame Spirit ſeems to be among you, that once was between <hi>Cox</hi> of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Church-Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>Knox</hi> of <hi>Scotland;</hi> when at <hi>Frankfort,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream zeal of one for the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and of the other againſt it, made them fall into preternatural heats. I am aſhamed to write the whole, but cover all with that of the holy Ghoſt concerning the great ſend between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 15 39.</note> 
               <hi>that ſharp was the contention between them.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice however, <hi>That the Common-prayer-man was the ſharpeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would ask them that have not yet learned <hi>Pauls</hi> directions, when contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were in the Church of God, about little things in Religion, as Meats, Drinks, and Holy-days, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Haſt thou Faith, have it to thy ſelf before
<pb facs="tcp:151471:4"/>God: Let every man be perſwaded in his own mind:</hi> What if <hi>Origen, Auguſtine,</hi> and many of the Ancient Fathers, and Holy Martyrs were now alive? would they have them ſilenced for ever, and caſt out of the Church, becauſe they had ſome Principles that rendred them uncapable to ſubſcribe and ſwear as ſome expect? When there is an Uniformity in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all mens Bodies, in the feature of all faces, in the found of all Voices, then, and not 'till then may we expect an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in the Opinions, and ſo practices of the People of God.</p>
            <p>Our Diviſions are the great ſtumbling-block to a Prophane world, who if we perſwade them to <hi>live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly,</hi> tell us, You are not of one mind; though our anſwer be ready, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are <hi>Phyſicians</hi> nor <hi>Lawyers,</hi> yet that man would not be himſelf that ſhould ſay, if my Body and my Eſtate be in never ſo great danger, I will hearken to none of them. Great have been the Controverſies of late years on foot about Succeſſion, if any man ſhould therfore ſay, Government is needleſs, 'tis fatal to the world; how ſoon might he be anſwer'd? If any man ſhould ſay, becauſe one man accounts a houſe of one figure beſt, and another of
<pb facs="tcp:151471:5"/>another figure, I will therefore dwell in no Houſe; Becauſe one thinks Cloaths of one colour and faſhion beſt, and another of another, I will therefore put on no Apparel; becauſe one man loves ſuch a diſh that another cares not for, therefore I will eat nothing; he were Diſtracted: Let ſuch mind the things wherein we agree, and then if they miſtake in the things about which we differ, they will be ſaved: We all grant Repentance, Faith, and a Holy Life neceſſary; <hi>Mind theſe things:</hi> Would to God I had ſpent ſome of the hours in enquiring how my Soul might be bowed down before God in Prayer, that I have ſpent in enquiring whether I ſhould Pray in my own words, or the words of others; that I had more enquired how I might come to the Lords Table, <hi>Hungring and Thirſting after Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> and leſs what geſture I ſhould there uſe.</p>
            <p>You know my Brethren, your own Judgments often change in the ſmaller matters of Religion, which may make you moderate towards them that <hi>diſſent</hi> from you, ſeeing you ſo <hi>often diſſent</hi> from your ſelves: As the Body changeth in a few years, old matter paſſeth away, and there comes a ſucceſſion of new; ſo every
<pb facs="tcp:151471:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>enquiring, thinking man knows, that what he thought lawful at one time, he hath thought unlawful at another, and cannot help it.</p>
            <p>Teſtifie my Brethren, teſtifie againſt the formal men of all your perſwaſions, who when they plead for the high things in Religion, do it with ſo much coldneſs, as if their words did freeze in their mouths; but when for their little noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are ſo full of rage and fury, as if wrath and envy had choſen their faces, to diſcover their complexion to the world; <hi>But remember you are Chriſtians, and Chriſtians muſt love one another. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus</hi> in his Speech to the Souldiers, when there was a mutiny among them,<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> ſaid, <hi>Divus Julius ſeditionem exercitus uno verbo compeſcuit, Quirites vocando;</hi> that <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> ended a ſedition in an Army, by one word, calling them <hi>Romans,</hi> he bad them remember they were <hi>Romans;</hi> ſo you are <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> If the hand have the Palſie, and ſhakes much, and can hardly hold any thing, who is preſently for Amputation or cutting it off? Learn you of <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1, 2. <hi>Him that is weak in the Faith, receive you, but not to doubtful diſputations: For one believeth that he may eat all things, another who is weak,
<pb facs="tcp:151471:6"/>eateth herbs:</hi> v. 13. <hi>Let us not therefore judge one another any more:</hi> v. 19. <hi>Let us therefore follow after the things that make for Peace, and the things whereby we may Edifie one another.</hi> I know not how my counſel may take with ſome of you; I know that he that cometh between two that are fighting, to part them, is ſometime beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by both: I know that ſome on the one hand will be offended, and charge me that I ſeem to countenance <hi>Superſtition;</hi> and others on the other hand will ſay that I favour <hi>Schiſm,</hi> but I matter not.</p>
            <p>The Proteſtant Church, the Veſſel in which we are, is ready to ſink, <hi>Lord ſave us, or elſe we periſh;</hi> God be merciful to thoſe deſperate Souls, who becauſe we cannot agree, therefore reject all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if a man at Sea, ſeeing the waves urgent, and hearing the winds roaring, ſhould ſay, if this 'tis to be in a Ship, I will never here abide, and ſo commit himſelf to the vaſt Ocean: So are they that reject all Religion, becauſe of the Contentions that are in the Church of God, and fall into Atheiſm and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs: Accept kindly of this plain Diſcourſe, devoid of all Embelliſhments of fine words and Phraſes, and take up with the great things of Religion, as you
<pb facs="tcp:151471:6"/>are directed by one that is of <hi>Pauls</hi> mind, who ſaith of himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20, 21, 22. <hi>And unto the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are under the Law, as under the Law, that I might gain them that are under the Law; to the weak be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came I as weak, that I might gain the weak: I am made</hi> (obſerve) <hi>all things to all men, that by all means I might ſave ſome:</hi> Had ſome weak headed Chriſtians among us ſeen him thus to do, perhaps they would have ſaid, that <hi>Paul</hi> often changed his Religion, or could not tell what Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be of; that he was not fixt, or a man of no Principles: Hear what he ſays elſewhere, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.33. <hi>Even as I pleaſe all men in all things, not ſeeking mine own profit, but the profit of many, that they might be ſaved:</hi> As far as I can, I am yours in your divers ways of worſhipping <hi>one Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> This I am reſolved on, that having been inſtrumental for the Converſion of many Souls, and I hope ſhall of many more, yet ungathered, that I will Preach Repentance, Faith and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grow</hi> my Brethren, <hi>Grow in Grace,</hi> that you may have that commendation given to the Church of <hi>Thyatira; I know thy Works, and Charity, and Service, and Faith,
<pb facs="tcp:151471:7"/>and thy Patience, and thy works, and the laſt to be more than the firſt,</hi> Rev. 2.19. But <hi>Oh! That my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of Tears, that I might weep day and night;</hi> not only for the Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Ungodly, but for the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs of the Righteous to all good works; I cry to you as in that Song, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Awake, awake Deborah: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, awake:</hi> Set about the work, to be more ſerious your ſelves, and to ſound an Alarm in the ears of a drowſie, ſleepy world, that they may be ſaved: That this may be your work, is the hearty De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and Prayer of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Brother, And Servant in our Lord,</hi> Samuel Young.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Glouceſter</hi> Goal, <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. 1683/4</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:151471:7"/>
            <head>TO ALL SEA-MEN, THAT ARE, <hi>Or would be Serious.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving in this Book, ſpoken of the chief things in Religion, I could not but call on you to mind theſe things your ſelves, and to put others in mind of them: I have you daily on my heart, before the Throne of Grace, that you that are ſerious may endeavour by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by Admonitions, by a good Example to make many ſo: You that are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, have taken Chriſts Preſs-money, have taken Chriſts Livery, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an engagement to <hi>Fight under his Banner, againſt Sin, the World and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> teſtifie againſt the Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Uncleanneſs, Sabbath-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:151471:8"/>Contempt of Prayer and Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scriptures, and other ſins many among you are guilty of. I know your great Objection, is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> That you ſhall be derided, if you ſo do; this I have heard from many of you.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Deride their Deriſion. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what is ſaid of <hi>Chriſt; and when his friends heard of it, they laid hold on him, for they ſaid, he is beſide himſelf,</hi> Mar. 3.21. If you are accounted mad by them that are really ſo; you have <hi>Chriſt</hi> for your Companion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is better be derided by men now, for the faithful diſcharge of your duty; than be derided by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Angels, and Saints, another day, for the neglect of your duty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Deriſion of ſome, may ſoon turn into imitation. They that at firſt mock at good counſel, may in time take it, and give it to others. I have ſeen an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, one laughing to ſee another mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſecret Prayer, and yet ſeeing conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and reſolution for that duty, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151471:8"/>
            <p>Remember, if you mourn not, if you pray not over the ungodly, their ſin is yours; if you reprove not, you are the cauſe of their damnation. I have read in the dreadful <hi>Tragedy</hi> of the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that one <hi>Dunchin,</hi> who had falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed them, one day paſſing by the Pit where ſixteen of them were caſt in, that he fell on it raging, and was diſtracted, conſidering there lay ſo many men he had ruined. How many go into Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whoſe Souls you have betrayed into the Infernal Pit, by your ſinful diſcourſe, or by your ſinful ſilence! Stop the mouth of the Swearer, and Blaſphemer as much as you can; James 3.4, 5, 6. <hi>Behold alſo the Ships, which though they be ſo great, and are driven with fierce winds, yet are they turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about with a very ſmall Helm, whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Governour liſteth. Even ſo the Tongue is a little member, and boaſteth great things: Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindleth. The tongue is a fire, a world of iniquity: — And it is ſet on fire of Hell.</hi> I wiſh you <hi>Moſes's</hi> Bleſſing, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.18, 19. <hi>Rejoice</hi> Zebulon, <hi>in thy going out, —Suck of the abundance of the Seas, and hid treaſures in the Sands.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151471:9"/>
            <p>Have you been as thoſe Mariners, <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.15.16. <hi>When Seas have raged, and ceaſed, made Vows to the Lord?</hi> Keep your Vows; Inſtruct poor Pagans in the way to God. Conſider the worth of your Souls and theirs. The better your <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> is, the more you fear Ship-wrack. O man thou art richly laden, that Veſſel, thy Body, carryes a Soul of greater value, than all the Treaſures upon earth: Let it never be ſaid of it, what was ſaid of that Ship, and men in it, Acts 27.20. <hi>That all hope of being ſaved, was taken away.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. Y.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="I" facs="tcp:151471:9"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALcinous</hi> the <hi>Platoniſt</hi> tells us, That <hi>Plato</hi> thought that the work of a Philoſopher conſiſted in three things, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which I think, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the liberty the Poet ſpeaks of,
<q>Nec verbum verbo curabis reddere fidus Interpres.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Herat. de</hi> Art. Poet.</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I may t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Engliſh:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In thinking well, in doing well, and in ſpeaking well.</hi> What their Philoſophy, which was much of their Natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, taught them; doth Chriſtianity, which is our ſupernatural Religion, teach us, but in a different way, and in a fuller manner. The deſign of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe is to help in this work. There are many things for Meditation of God,
<pb n="II" facs="tcp:151471:10"/>his Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> many practical Directions for a holy uſeful life, ſeveral helps to ſpeak to God, and for God. I know dangerous it is, for a man in my circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to be a Writer: But I care not if my counſel be accepted, what becomes of my perſon. I am perſwading the World to play the Chriſtian, to play the Man: As <hi>Solomon</hi> brings in Wiſdom ſpeaking, ſo do I, <hi>Unto you O men, do I call, and my voice is unto the Sons of men.</hi> Are you men, learn to act according to the excellency, and dignity of your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Let me beſeech thoſe, into whoſe hands this Book may come, if they have given up themſelves to the Immoralities of the Age, Drunkenneſs, Adultery, Swearing, Oppreſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that have all vices, that may make their lives a full Syſteme of wickedneſs; Vices, the nanning of which may ſeem to corrupt the Air we breathe in; Vices, that need little more to their confutation, than to be thought on; I ſay, let me perſwade you to conſider: Is Sin an evil thing, Grace a deſirable thing? Is God, and your Souls to be minded above all things, or not? If not, why do you
<pb n="III" facs="tcp:151471:10"/>ſay they are? If they are, why do you not live as thoſe that thus believe? I do not deſpair but that ſome, who are guilty of the unpreſidented Sins of the times, Sins of the first Edition; if they would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, they may yet learn to walk <hi>ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent World.</hi> I know ſuch are ready to ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Religion is abuſed to very bad purpoſes by ſome.</p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>I Anſwer, And uſed to very good purpoſes by others. Is</hi> Rhetorick <hi>to be deſpiſed, becauſe by it ſome bad men learn to colour a bad cauſe; as well as ſome good men to flouriſh a good cauſe? Is</hi> Logick <hi>to be deſpiſed, becauſe ſome learn to diſpute</hi> Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; <hi>as well as others</hi> Topically? <hi>Is the light of the Sun to be deſpiſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one ſteals by it; as another works in his Calling? How many men had lived as</hi> Incarnate Devils, <hi>that now live as</hi> Terreſtrial Angels, <hi>had not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion healed their Natures, and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated their Lives! Remember, Sin is a great part of the miſery and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of theſe men. They are</hi>
               <pb n="IV" facs="tcp:151471:11"/>out God, <hi>his Grace, and Love, and content to be ſo; they ſerve the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Sin, and are glad of the work. The Lord bring in ſuch, as their Elder Brother in the Goſpel, that was healed of his diſtraction, and was placed in his right mind</hi> at the Feet of Jeſus.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151471:11"/>
            <head>SOME Priſon Meditations AND DIRECTIONS ON Several Subjects.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Fall of Man.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>THat the finding out of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, is neceſſary in order to a Cure; is not more true of the Natural Diſtempers of our Bodies, than of the Spiritual Diſtempers of our Souls. The Apoſtle mentions the Fall of man at large to the <hi>Romans,</hi> to make way for the diſcovery of the Neceſſary and Excellency of a Saviour. <hi>Ron,</hi> 5. In the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151471:12"/>Fall of man, I ſhall conſider, that we all were in the Firſt Man, as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.9.10. <hi>Levi is ſaid to pay Tithes to Melchiſedeck, as he was in the loyns of his Father Abraham.</hi> So we may be ſaid to eat Forbidden Fruit, as we were in the loyns of our Father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> We were in him, as a Nation in their King. <hi>Adam</hi> was our Repre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: If he had ſtood, we had had the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſit of his obedience, though he, not we obeyed: So he diſobeying, we are brought under the Curſe, though he and not we offended. It is in vain in war, if Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects be taken, to ſay, our King proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made the War, not we; we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſented to it. If the Poſterity of a Traitor be diſinherited, it is in vain for them to plead, Our Father, not we, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired the death of the Prince, we were not then born. Beſides, the nature of man by the Fall was corrupt, <hi>and a clean thing cannot come out of an unclean.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job. 14.4.</note> It is true indeed what God ſaid by <hi>Ezekiel, The Children ſhall not bear the Iniquity of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 19.20.</note> If the Father ſin alone it is ſo, but this is not our Caſe; for we find our Principles, and ſo Practices corrupted. <hi>Adam</hi> was but one man <hi>perſonally,</hi> but he was all men <hi>potentially,</hi> and <hi>originally.</hi> I ſhall in order conſider,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151471:12"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. What we were before the Fall.</item>
                        <item>2. What Sin we were guilty of in the Fall.</item>
                        <item>3. What miſery we brought on our ſelves after the Fall. I may ſometimes name <hi>Adam</hi> onely, but it muſt be thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that <hi>we</hi> all were <hi>He.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. What <hi>Adam</hi> was before he fell. <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Gen.</hi> 5.2. are both called <hi>Adam, Male and Female created he them, and bleſſed them, and called their name Adam:</hi> In the day when they were Created they were one, though not by a <hi>Phyſical,</hi> yet by a <hi>Conjugal</hi> Union; they were two diſtinct perſons, yet one by nearneſs of relation; and ſo I may conſider them both, though ſometimes I name one only, as I ſee occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Before the Fall, great were the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges they had for their Bodie; and Souls: Of the firſt ſort.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Their Bodies were ſound and free from all diſtempers, bodies that could not be diſturbed by any outward colds or heats, or by any inward malignity or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. <hi>ult.</hi> Ask the ſick and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthy, that are chained by many pains in Head, Stomack, what this mercy was.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. All the Creatures were in ſubjection to him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28, 29, 30. God gave man <hi>Dominion over the Birds of the air, and over the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151471:13"/>Beaſts of the earth, and over the Fiſh of the ſea, and over the living things that creep on the earth:</hi> The Creatures ſaw ſuch a luſtre in the countenance of man, that they fear'd him; ſo much majeſty yet appears, though ſin hath leſſen'd it, that the Beaſts fear us not a little: For venomous Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they either had no venome, or that venom could not hurt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He was ſeated in a pleaſant Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.8. <hi>And the Lord God planted a Garden eaſtward in Eden, and there he put the man, whom he had formed.</hi> The Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of which place we read in the 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>verſes.</hi> Where he was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, or where <hi>Eden</hi> was, a Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath ſpent much time to enquire.<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Walt. Rawley</hi> Hiſt. of World.</note> That <hi>Paradiſe</hi> was not the whole world, is clear from <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24. <hi>So he drove out the man;</hi> not ſure out of the world, for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> lived, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.5. <hi>nine Hundred and thirty years.</hi> For the idle notions that the Rivers ſignifie virtues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I will not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them with a confutation.</p>
                  <p>The good things of the Soul were theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It was enricht with wonderful know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.19, 20. When God brought the Creatures to <hi>Adam,</hi> he on the firſt ſight gave names to them; that is, names ſignificative, or expreſſive of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151471:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>as if we ſhould call a Lion Rage, a Lamb Meek, a Dove Innocent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His Knowledge much exceeded ours; his was habitual, ours acquired; his was compleat, ours imperfect; His knowledg was as much above the knowledg of the wiſeſt man on earth, as the knowledg of a wiſe man above the knowledge of a Child.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He had a perfection of Holineſs, not only a perfection of degrees, but of parts: he was perfect, not only if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Perfection in oppoſition to Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, as <hi>Abraham, Noah,</hi> and many Saints in Scripture are ſaid to be perfect: But perfect in oppoſition to any defect, or imperfection. <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe was as an Angel in Heaven, was as free from any Sin or contempt of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He had frequent, and immediate, and full Communion with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16, 17. God ſpeaks to man, and man to God without any fear, or dread. What an honour is it for a mean man to have the ear of a Prince, or great man at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure! Hence it was that <hi>Paradiſe</hi> was a lower Heaven; which makes ſome think, if man had not ſinned, he had there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for ever.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We come to conſider what Sins we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151471:14"/>were guilty of in the Fall. Man had ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad thoughts of a good God; very good thoughts of a bad Devil; very high thoughts of low Self, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. They made God a Lyar, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Devil as a Speaker of truth; <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. God ſaid, <hi>In the day you eat thereof, you ſhall die, Gen.</hi> 3.3. The Devil ſaid, <hi>You ſhall not ſurely die, Gen.</hi> 3.4. The Woman ſaid, <hi>Leſt you die.</hi> God affirms, the Devil denies, and the woman doubts. Many Temptations <hi>Adam</hi> had that we know not; Now this was by Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to give God the Lye. How tedious is it among men to be called a Lyar, and what effuſion of blood hath it cauſed! Now the Devil the Father of Lies is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved more than God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They lookt on God as unworthy to be their Commander, and took the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil for their Councellour: God muſt ſtand by, the Devil takes place. They choſe this God, or Guide, for themſelves and Poſterity; hence it is the Devil is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Apoſtle, <hi>The God of this World,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They thought it unbecoming them to be reſtrained by any Law. <hi>They ſhould be as Gods, Gen.</hi> 3.5. That there was ſome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151471:14"/>hidden vertue in the Tree, that would make the Eaters of its fruit, more like an abſolute God, than God would have them be; and therefore God forbad the touching that Tree. This was the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We ſhall conſider what Miſeries we brought on our ſelves after the Fall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We were deprived of the Image of the Bleſſed God: According to ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural endowments, it was totally gone, there was not one <hi>Spark of Grace</hi> left; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of holineſs remained in man. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to natural endowments, this Image was in part gone; much wiſdom, much power over the Creatures was gone, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.7. They were as naked in their Souls, as in their Bodies. As <hi>Aaron</hi> in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Golden Calf, is ſaid to <hi>make the people naked,</hi> Exod. 32.25.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We were caſt out of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> among the reſt of the Beaſts, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims</hi> appeared in Shape like an Ox. Now man by Sin, had made himſelf like the Beaſts that periſh; and therefore God ſends him to be their companion. He is not now in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> but in a Wilderneſs, not in a place of pleaſure, but of toyl and ſorrow, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We are naturally inclined to all ſin,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151471:15"/>and ſo expoſed to all Judgments. The Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is clouded with errour; the judgment fails, both in directing what is to be done, and judging of the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of what is done: The affections are carnal: In a word, the Soul is blinded,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> nay, ſome ſo blind as hardly to ſee the Being of God: That what once God ſaid to <hi>Adam,</hi> they are ready to ſay to God, <hi>Where art thou? Gen.</hi> 2.17. I know it is enquired, what Death was threatned in thoſe words,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
                     <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die.</hi> Some think only the death of the Body. But I thus argue, That Death that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed mans ſin was there threatned, and the death that followed was the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural death of the Body, the ſpiritual death of the Soul, and the eternal death both of Body and Soul; and therefore all was threatned in thoſe words, <hi>Thou ſhalt die.</hi> Is it reaſonable to think, that the great Law-maker put more in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, than there was in the Threat? In <hi>Adam,</hi> you find no confeſſion of <hi>Sin</hi> to God, but adding Sin to Sin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10. When he fled, God calls to him, how doth he reply? <hi>I heard thy voice in the Garden, and I was afraid, becauſe I was naked, and I hid my ſelf:</hi> As if he had ſaid, I am hid,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151471:15"/>becauſe I heard thy voice; it is exceeding piercing, it is the voice of a God; and I am but Fleſh and Blood, and I cannot bear it. But did he not hear Gods voice before, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16, 17. when God gave him a charge, <hi>not to eat of the Tree in the midſt of the Garden? I was naked,</hi> was another Excuſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.25. Were they not before both naked, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed? When God told <hi>Adam</hi> plainly of his Sin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Haſt thou eaten of the Tree, whereof I commanded thee, that thou ſhouldſt not eat?</hi> One would think, now there is no room for an excuſe: verſe 12. you read, <hi>The woman thou gaveſt to be with me, ſhe gave me of the Tree, and I did eat.</hi> He layes it on the woman, but the woman could not compell, though ſhe did tempt: Nay, rather than take the blame to himſelf, he layes it on God; <hi>Thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt.</hi> If thou hadſt not given me the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhe had not tempted, nor I eaten. Few know or conſider the hardning na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Sin. One might have expected, he ſhould have cryed, Lord pity me, Lord contrive a way to ſhew mercy, if there be any; or if none, Lord thou art juſt in all the evil that ſhall come upon me. So was man expoſed to all Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments temporal, diſtempers, troubles, loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151471:16"/>death, and at laſt to eternal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>where the Worm dyeth not, and the Fire is never quenched.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now to theſe Meditations, I ſhall add a few Directions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Mourn over your ſelves and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, fallen into ſin and miſery. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt <hi>Adam</hi> are in vain; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt God are worſe. It was neceſſary, as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſayes, that the will of man ſhould be <hi>flexibilis in utramque partem:</hi> God having made man, it was convenient he ſhould put him on Tryal of Obedience. God gave him but one Law, not many; an eaſie one, not diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult; a negative one, not poſitive; no thanks had been to <hi>Adam</hi> to obey, if he could not have diſobeyed. Conſider it, and it fell out that he ſinned. What have we loſt in loſing <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and the bleſſings there! When <hi>Ziklag</hi> was burnt, what an outcry was there! 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.3, 4. <hi>So David and his men came to the City, and behold, it was burnt with fire; and their Wives, and their Sons, and their Daughters were taken Captives:</hi> What follows? <hi>Then David and the People that were with him, lift up their Voice and wept, until they had no
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151471:16"/>Power to weep.</hi> What was <hi>Ziklag</hi> to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe?</hi> what was the Captivity of the Body, to that of the Soul? How ſadly do men look back on a burnt Houſe, and Treaſures there; and weep bitterly!</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Cry againſt the Tempter, that you may through Grace out-wit him. Was he too hard for man in innocency, how much more now? If any man wants wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, let him ask it of God:<note place="margin">James 5.</note> Cry to God againſt Satan, as <hi>David</hi> againſt <hi>Ahitho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> that God would confound the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of <hi>Ahithophel;</hi> ſo Lord,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.31.</note> confound the Devices of the evil one.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Strive againſt all Objections againſt God in this matter. Though the Act Phyſically conſidered is of God; yet not Morally. And though it is true, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Cauſes cannot act without the firſt, <hi>aliquid Poſitioum;</hi> yet they may <hi>aliquid delinquens.</hi> We have learnt of <hi>Adam</hi> to lay all on God. To them that deny any thing of Predetermination, I humbly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this to Conſideration. Whether it be rational to imagine, that it depended upon ſo pitiful, and weak, and change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a thing as <hi>Adams</hi> Will, without Gods Determination? Whether Chriſt ſhould come into the World, and dye, and ſo be a Saviour? Whether the Providences
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151471:17"/>of God in the World, ſhould be ſuch as they are? Whether the greateſt part of Mankind ſhould be in Hell for ever, and thouſands before the Throne, Praiſing God for a Redeemer? However, <hi>Let every Mouth be ſtopped before God. Luther</hi> ſays, I put off queſtions about Gods Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinations, with that of <hi>Christ</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi> when he asked an unneceſſary que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion about <hi>John;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 22.23.</note> 
                     <hi>What is that to thee? follow thou me; Officium agamus,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Loci. Com.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; diſputationes de Predestinatione Seponamus:</hi> Rom. 11.33. <hi>How unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are his Judgments, and his ways paſt finding out!</hi> Many would ſearch out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable Judgments, and find out ways paſt finding out. I will not cut a knot that I cannot untie. We that cannot ſolve the <hi>Phoenomena</hi> of Nature; how can we ſatisfie our ſelves about the great Myſteries of Religion?</p>
                  <p>We are by Nature Children of wrath,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.</note> and let us not ſo curiouſly enquire, how Original ſin got into our Heart, as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully enquire how to get it out. For that Objection againſt Sin in Infancy:</p>
                  <p>Obj. <hi>Omne peccatum est voluntarium.</hi> Every ſin is Voluntary. <hi>Mel.</hi> in his <hi>Com. Places,</hi> ſays, that muſt be underſtood <hi>in civilibus Delictis,</hi> in civil Offences among
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151471:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>men: and yet ſin is voluntary in Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>quia</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) <hi>eo delectamur,</hi> becauſe we delight in it.</p>
                  <p>As for ſuch fooliſh Queſtions, Whether if <hi>Adam</hi> had begotten Children before he fell, Sin had been imputed to thoſe Children; we will not waſte time to conſider them. <hi>Catarinus</hi> affirmed, <hi>Soto</hi> denyed,<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                     </note> as <hi>F. P.</hi> ſays. Run to <hi>Christ,</hi> who by once Suffering can ſave you, as <hi>Adam</hi> by once ſinning hath deſtroyed you. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>For as by one mans Diſobedience ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were made Sinners; ſo by the Obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous. Chriſt was obedient unto Death,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> 
                     <hi>even the Death of the Croſs.</hi> The Law is in full force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every ungodly man: God hath ſtill his Power of commanding, though we have thrown away our Power of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying. God ſees more ſin in one wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thought, than we do in actual Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; in one covetous thought, than we do in open Theft. Oh then run to <hi>Jeſus</hi> that juſtifieth, that ſanctifieth, that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. He is our <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that hath all the Store-houſes of Proviſion, in a time of Famine: As the diſtreſſed <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſaid to him, let us ſay to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Gen. 47.18, 19. <hi>We will not hide it from my Lord, our money is gone; — Give us bread, let us be Servants
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151471:18"/>unto Pharaoh. We will not, nay, we cannot hide it from our Lord:</hi> All is gone; let us have Grace from him, that we may ſerve our God; and all Believers muſt ſay to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as they to <hi>Joſeph, v.</hi> 25. <hi>Thou haſt ſaved our lives, let us find Grace in the ſight of our Lord.</hi> When ſin had ſlain us, <hi>Chriſt</hi> had Compaſſion on us, as <hi>David</hi> had on his Son, when his own Folly had ruin'd him. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33. <hi>And the King was much moved, and wept, and as he went, thus he ſaid, O my Son Abſalom, my Son, my Son Abſalom; would God I had dyed for thee, O Abſalom my Son, my Son.</hi> Yet <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſought his Fathers Crown and Life; and we would be as Gods. Chriſt feem'd to ſay over us, Would to God I might dye for thee; and indeed, <hi>it pleaſed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bruiſe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.10.</note> —I believe that <hi>Adam</hi> through this <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſaved, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16. God immediately on the fall applyed himſelf to him, and promiſed a Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> makes <hi>Adam</hi> a Figure of him that was to come.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.14.</note> If ſin and guilt might have made any man pine away, <hi>Adam</hi> had been the man, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the Flood-gates of Sin and Wrath to break in upon the World, and was the ruine of the greateſt part of his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; yet hearing of a Saviour, he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151471:18"/>lived almoſt a thouſand years. <hi>We are not ſo to mourn for ſin, as to forget to rejoyce in Chriſt our Saviour.</hi> Of this bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, I ſhall ſpeak in the next Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Sufferings of Chriſt.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>GOD is more pleaſed with the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than diſpleaſed with the Sin of <hi>Adam:</hi> he more loveth us as the Children of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us as the Children of <hi>Adam.</hi> We muſt often conſider the Death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and be affected with it. It was Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyed of old,<note place="margin">Zach. 12.10.</note> 
                     <hi>They ſhall look on him whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him, as one mourneth for the loſs of an only Son, and ſhall be in bitterneſs for him, as one that is in bitterneſs for his firſt-born.</hi> And O what wringing of hands, what deep Groans, what doleful Out-cryes are there made oftentimes for the loſs of an onely Child, or Firſt-born!<note place="margin">Act 2.37.</note> What made <hi>Peters</hi> Converts to be <hi>prickt at the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151471:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Heart,</hi> but the Preaching of a crucified <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall here conſider, (1.) What Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying was. (2.) Who were the Agents in this Work. (3.) <hi>Who,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> he was on whom this Cruelty was acted.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For the manner of Crucifying. There was <hi>Lignum Geminum,</hi> as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Weems</hi> ſpeaks at large in his <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Synagogue:</hi> The Croſs had four things; <hi>Arrectarium,</hi> or Main-tree; <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellum,</hi> the Tree where the feet were Nailed; <hi>Lignum tranſverſum,</hi> whereunto their Arms were faſtned with Cords, and there Nail'd; <hi>Vertex,</hi> the Title with the Inſcription above the Head. This way of putting to Death, was ſo ſhameful and ſo lingring, that the <hi>Romans</hi> inflicted it on none but Slaves, or the vileſt ſort of men. <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> in Honour of Chriſt, took away this Puniſhment. Chriſt had carryed his own Croſs (as all Crucified Perſons did) but they had ſo weakned him,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.32.</note> that they made <hi>Simon of Cyrene</hi> to carry it, not out of Kindneſs to Chriſt, but hatred; leſt he being ſo ſeverely handled before, ſhould faint by the way, and their blood-ſhot eyes loſe the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of beholding him tormented on the Croſs. The <hi>Romans</hi> call'd this Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151471:19"/>
                     <hi>Servile Supplicium,</hi> for the reaſon before-named.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We come to conſider the Actors in this woful Tragedy. They were not the prophane Gentiles, or common Rabble among the Jews, that only did this; but the High Prieſt, the Scribes, the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They that had ſo long prayed, and waited for his coming. Before he came into the world, the Devout Jews thought Bleſſed were the eyes that ſhould ſee the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in the Fleſh. It was a Petition commonly made by them, in their Giving of Thanks at their Tables; Let our eyes be made worthy to ſee the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in the Fleſh. What cryes were there,<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.1.</note> 
                     <hi>O that he would rend the Heavens, and come down! Malachi</hi> that cloſed up the Old Teſtament, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, how though they longed for him, yet they could not ſtand before him.<note place="margin">Mal. 3.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I will ſend my Meſſenger, and the Lord whom ye ſeek, ſhall ſuddenly come to his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even the Meſſenger of the covenant in whom ye delight:</hi> But what follows? <hi>But who may abide the day of his coming? And who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth? For he is like Refiners Fire, and as Full<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs Sope.</hi> He dealt too plainly with the world con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151471:20"/>their Sin and Duty, to be welcom'd by them. They expected a <hi>Meſſias,</hi> to deliver them from the power of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> and God ſent a <hi>Meſſias</hi> to deliver from the power of the Devil.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They that were acquainted with the Law and the Prophets; That might by Types and Propheſies have known that Chriſt was the promiſed Saviour.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They that heard his Doctrine, and ſaw his Miracles. His Doctrine was ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Heavenly, reaching the Heart and Soul; His Miracles were not done in a Corner; as feeding many thouſands with a few Loaves, his raiſing <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the Dead.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We now come to conſider <hi>who,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> he was who thus ſuffered.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. He that did their Bodies ſo much good: <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>for a good man ſome would even dare to die: Though ſcarcely for a Righteous man,</hi> Rom. 5.7. That is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider him as righteous before God, and ſo few love him ſo well, as to die for him; but conſider him as good to man, ſo ſome would loſe their lives for him. But here they were ſo far from dying for this good man, that they contrived his death. He cured all ſorts of men, of all ſorts of Diſtempers; he raiſed the Dead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151471:20"/>
                  <p n="2">2. He that came to ſave Souls from endleſs burnings, and to bring them to endleſs Bleſſedneſs.<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.10.</note> It is not more true that our Bodies and Souls are now in the world, than that they had been in end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs miſery had not Chriſt dyed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that was God. God ſuffered in the <hi>Perſon, Acts</hi> 20.28. though not in the <hi>Nature.</hi> Hence it is, that his Temporal Sufferings were as much as our Eternal would have been. Chriſt had his <hi>Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> but not his <hi>Substance</hi> from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who begat him in reſpect of Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality, not of Eſſence. The dignity of his perſon, made the Sin of crucifying him ſo great. I will ſuppoſe, that all the Saints in Heaven and Earth were met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yea that all the Angels were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate and among them, and that a man or number of men ſhould murther them all; this Sin were no ſin in compariſon of what I now ſpeak of, the Crucifying of the <hi>Lord of Glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Christ</hi> ſuffered from firſt to laſt. In his Birth; for the <hi>Ancient of Dayes</hi> to be born in time, for the Eternal God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Babe, this is ſoon ſaid, but who underſtands the depth of theſe things? <hi>Luke</hi> 2.12. <hi>And this ſhall be a ſign unto you, you ſhall find the Babe wrapped in ſwadling-cloaths,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151471:21"/>lying in a Manger:</hi> yet was all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the infinite wiſdom of God. Had <hi>Christ</hi> been the Son of <hi>Herod,</hi> or <hi>Caeſar,</hi> then it had been no wonder, that all the world went out after him; but that one ſo obſcurely born, ſhould carry the world before him, was wonderful! <hi>John</hi> when in <hi>Patmos,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 11.15.</note> foreſaw, <hi>That the Kingdoms of the World would become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and his Chriſt;</hi> which then was very unlikely in outward appearance. He was ſorely tempted by the Devil, we read at large in <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. Gods end in all we have, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi> Ask the Saints what Suffering this is, that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſweat under this Saddle, when they are tempted to hate God, or diſtruſt him, have ſuch ſuggeſtions as are not fit to be named.</p>
                  <p>He was deſpiſed in his common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with men:<note place="margin">Luk. 8.20.</note> 
                     <hi>The Foxes had their holes, and the Birds of the Air their neſts, but Jeſus had not where to lay his head. He was revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as one that had a Devil;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 10.20. Mark 2.16. Luk. 22.44.</note> 
                     <hi>and was made as a Friend of Publicans and Sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In his Agonies in the Garden, <hi>He ſweat drops of Blood,</hi> though it were ſuch a cold ſeaſon, that one might think would have ſtruck the Blood inward: It was a cold
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151471:21"/>time, for <hi>Peter</hi> ſtood to warm himſelf. Our Sin was the heavy burthen that lay upon him.</p>
                  <p>When, and after he was Betrayed: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed he was by a Friend, a Boſome-friend; to be Betrayed, and that in point of Life, and all by an intimate acquaintance, goes near the Heart. What <hi>David</hi> ſaid to him that betrayed, might <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſay to <hi>Judas: Had it been an Enemy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.13, 14.</note> 
                     <hi>I could have born it; but it was thou, my Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we took ſweet Counſel together, and walked together as Friends.</hi> He was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely handled by Souldiers, who bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd his Ears with Blaſphemy, as well as tormented his Body: when he was on the Croſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. <hi>v.</hi> 39, 40. they wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Heads, tell him of what he was accuſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 41, 42, 43. The great men revile him; when uſually men that ſcarce pray all the year long for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they ſee any infamous Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal executed, they never tell him in a way of ſcoffing, of his Fault or Crime, but ſay, God be merciful to his Soul. At laſt, Chriſt cryes out, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.46. <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> We muſt warily underſtand this, not as if God had forſaken Chriſt in reſpect of <hi>Strength,</hi> for an Angel was ſent to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151471:22"/>ſtrengthen him;<note place="margin">Luk. 22.33.</note> nor in reſpect of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> nor of <hi>Complacency;</hi> but God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him as to preſent comfort in a great meaſure. Imagine you ſtood as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Women at the Croſs, and ſaw this. I now come to lay down a few Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Look on, and wonder. <hi>Are theſe things ſo?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Then great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs, God manifeſted in the fleſh!</hi> If it be a Myſtery, it cannot be fathomed. Wonder at what Chriſt <hi>is,</hi> and at what he <hi>doth:</hi> What he <hi>is, Prov.</hi> 30.4. It was the wiſe mans Probleme, or hard Queſtion, <hi>What is his name, or his Sons name, if thou canſt tell? His Name is called Wonderful, Iſa.</hi> 9.6. Wonder that the Divinity did not ſwallow up the Humanity, that the <hi>fire</hi> and the <hi>buſh</hi> can ſo well agree together. All the Attributes of God are given to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all the Works of God ſpoken of him, as of Creation, Sanctification, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification: Therefore Chriſt is God not only by name, or <hi>ſecundum divi;</hi> but God by Nature. He was God that he might ſatisfie, he was Man that he might ſuffer. Wonder at what he <hi>doth. Patereulus</hi> ſays, that when the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Attica,</hi> the <hi>Pythian</hi> God told them,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151471:22"/>that that Army whoſe General was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſhould conquer: <hi>Codrus depoſita veſte regia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Codrus</hi> laying aſide his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Robes, went among his enemies, and was ſlain by them. Our King on <hi>Maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Thurſday,</hi> (ſo call'd, as ſome ſay, becauſe of the Command of Love, Chriſt gave his Diſciples before his Paſſion, <hi>Mandatum novum do vobis,</hi>) I ſay our King uſeth to waſh the feet of as many poor People as he hath lived years, and yet not the leſs a King for this humble act. Our <hi>Lord Jeſus the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> dyed that we might live, abaſed himſelf, that he might exalt us. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 126.1, 2. When God delivered the Church out of <hi>Babylon</hi> by <hi>Cyrus, they were like men that dreamed.</hi> How much more ſhould we be Aſtoniſhed at our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from Sin and Satan by Jeſus Chriſt!</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let Love be attactive of Love. Let the Love of Jeſus to us, make us to Love him. I have read of <hi>Agilmond</hi> King of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> that one day he went a fiſhing, and ſaw a Babe ſpraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Water (perhaps a baſe child) he took it up, and made it his adopted Son, and called him <hi>Lama,</hi> and left him his Crown and Kingdom: You may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151471:23"/>imagine what delight this <hi>Lama</hi> took in ſeeing of King <hi>Algilmond</hi> whilſt he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and in thinking and ſpeaking of this King after he was dead. How excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently doth God expreſs his love to the poor <hi>Jews</hi> of old! Ezek. 16.4, 5, 6. <hi>As for thy Nativity, in the day thou waſt born, thy Navel was not cut, neither waſt thou waſhed in water; — None eye pitied thee to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe unto thee, to have compaſſion on thee; but thou waſt caſt out into the open field, to the loathing of thy perſon, in the day that thou waſt born. And when I paſſed by thee, and ſaw thee polluted in thy own Blood; I ſaid unto thee when thou wast in thy Blood, live;</hi> (And leſt this ſhould be ſoon paſſed over, the Holy Ghoſt bids them, as it were, ſtand and hear it the ſecond time,) <hi>Yoa, I ſaid unto thee, when thou waſt in thy Blood, live:</hi> When <hi>Tiberius</hi> was in a Village named <hi>Spelunca,</hi> Stones fell from the houſe where he was: <hi>Sejanus genu, vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, manibuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuper Caeſarem ſuſpenſis oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit ſeſe, ſatis incidentibus;</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus: Sejanus</hi> covered the Emperour, that if the Stones fell where they were, <hi>Sejanus</hi> might die, and not the Emperour; which as the Hiſtorian obſerves, made the Emperour ever after to love <hi>Sejanus,</hi> though he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him not before. The wrath of God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151471:23"/>fell from Heaven, becauſe of mans ſin: <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath embraced the Sinner and that wrath hath fallen on him, that elſe had cruſhed us. O let us love him, let us not be ſatisfied till we find our hearts burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in love.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Crucifie Sin, that crucified Chriſt. Be the death of thoſe Sins, that were the death of Jeſus; Pride, Wrath, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and every abominable thing, which the Soul of God hates: Rom. 6.6. <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, that our Old man is crucified with Chriſt, that the body of ſin might be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerve ſin:</hi> Sin is onely deſtroyed by his death; had not Chriſt dyed for us, we could no more have killed our Corruptions, or been made Saints, than the Devils can ceaſe to be Devils, and become Angels.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Come to God as thoſe that expect to be juſtified no other way, but by Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs: In him is God well pleaſed with Believers. The Names given to Chriſt are in Scripture given to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, as Son of God, an Heir, King, yea the name <hi>Chriſt;</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12.</note> 
                     <hi>As many Members make one Body, even ſo is Chriſt:</hi> Where it is underſtood not of <hi>Chriſt perſonally,</hi> but <hi>myſtically,</hi> for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or the Church of Chriſt. Now as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151471:24"/>
                     <hi>Adams</hi> ſins is imputed to us, though he, and not we diſobeyed; ſo <hi>Chriſts</hi> Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is imputed to us, though he, not we obeyed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. laſt verſe; Though <hi>Adams</hi> Sin be imputed to us, yet we were not the firſt ſinners, nor the involvers of all Mankind into Miſery: So, though Chriſts Righteouſneſs be imputed to us, yet we are not therefore Saviours or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators. We are often commanded to be ſanctifyed, but not to be Juſtified; for Juſtification is Gods own work without us. The Grace of Chriſt, that is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe of our Sanctification, and is the eſſential cauſe, the matter and form of our Juſtification. And therefore when God is ſaid to reward men according to their works, it ſhews the order of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not the Cauſe; <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no Scripturae exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo, iſta quaeſtio eluceſcit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Calv. Inſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> ſaith <hi>Calvin:</hi> One example in Scripture, ſhall make it clear. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.5. The Promiſe made to <hi>Abram</hi> in Uncircumciſion, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17. is there made again on his Offering up of <hi>Iſaac; By my ſelf have I ſworn, becauſe thou hast done this thing — I will multiply thy Seed as the Stars of the Heavens:</hi> Now his Obedience was not the Cauſe of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, for <hi>Abraham</hi> had it before, but was an occaſion of renewing it at that time:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151471:24"/>God rewarded his good works, and ſo will ours, with Bleſſings promiſed before the good works were done. Heaven is an Inheritance of Children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> If good works juſtifie not, what need is there to preſs after them? Take <hi>Luthers anſwer:</hi> This is juſt as if we ſhould ſay, Money Juſtifies not, therefore throw it away; our Hands juſtifie us not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cut them off:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luthers</hi> Comment on the <hi>Epiſt. Gala.</hi>
                     </note> We muſt attribute (ſaith he) to every thing its proper Work, and Office. A Woman may not wear a Mans Apparel, nor a Man a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. The Sun ſhineth by day, and the Moon by night: So he. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art no more a Servant, but a Son; and if a Son, then an Heir of God by Chriſt.</hi> An Heir is not Agent, but Patient; hath all by Birth, not by Labour; no more than to be born. <hi>The Promiſe, being of Grace, is ſure to all the ſeed:</hi> It was not ſure to <hi>Adam,</hi> he had his Treaſure in his own hand, and ſo loſt it; but we have ours in the hand of Chriſt. Juſtification, and Sanctification are not ſeparated, though they be diſtinguiſhed: He that is juſtified will be holy,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> and <hi>zealous of good works.</hi> The Objection, that we are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to good works is in vain. King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Eighth, in his Book againſt <hi>Luther,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151471:25"/>de Septem Sacramentis,</hi> (for which Book the Pope gave him the Title of <hi>Defender of the Faith</hi>) chargeth our Reformers, with pleading for all manner of Sins from this Doctrine; but how true, the world now knows. If any of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are offended, I beſeech them to read the Homilies about theſe matters, and <hi>Biſhop Downhams</hi> large Folio of <hi>Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and they will find my opinion not different from the old Proteſtants, thô I confeſs different from the Opinion of ſome of the late new Proteſtants, both <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Non-conformiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. If you are through Chriſt related unto God, give Chriſt the Glory, and take to your ſelves the comfort of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. We are ſaid to be <hi>of his Fleſh and Bone;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 5.31, 32.</note> to be <hi>married to Chriſt;</hi> Now if the Husband be beyond Sea, thouſands of miles from the Wife, yet they are one: So is God and a Believer,<note place="margin">Joh. 17.21.</note> though God be in Heaven, and he upon the earth.</p>
                  <p>Remember Chriſtians what <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath done for you: He hath paid your debts that you could never do. If a woman were in debt Thouſands of Pounds, and by working hard every day, ſhould pay Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence now and then; yet ſhe could never all her life time pay the Sum: But if a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151471:25"/>Rich Man come, and pay down the whole and take the woman to wife, he doth that in a day, which ſhe could never have done in her life time. Chriſt hath done that in a little time, that we had been do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of to eternity: He ſatisfied Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. The Dignity of the perſon, makes the Sufferings of ſuch great value. Give God the glory, that you hear of Chriſt that you believe in him: pity and pray for the poor <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe eyes are not yet opened. They have not been a Church, nor Nation for Sixteen Hundred years paſt.</p>
                  <p>When they were under the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity, it was but Seventy years, and they had Prophets to Comfort them; but now none comes from God to them, which Conſideration hath converted ſome of them, <hi>Schamaria,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> two great <hi>Jews</hi> by <hi>Luther.</hi> I know no Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (in my little Converſe with them) that ſo convinceth them, that they have not been the Church of God for ſo long time. <hi>Eleazer Bargiſha</hi> a Converted <hi>Jew,</hi> in his vain hopes of the Jewiſh <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> hath diſcovered many of their vain Dreams, and Dr. <hi>Addiſon</hi> in his <hi>Hiſt.</hi> of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Stir up thine Affections, O Chriſtian, let thy Heart burn within thee,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151471:26"/>in the Conſideration of the Excellencies of Chriſt. Muſe a little on theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scriptures: <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to us by his Son, whom he appointed Heir of all things:</hi> Great Heirs are deſired in Marriage; will not this do? Once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.3. <hi>In him are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge.</hi> We delight in men of Wiſdom, though where they know one thing, they are ignorant of many. Now <hi>Chriſt is the Wiſdom of God;</hi> will not this do? I will try once more, <hi>and a threefold Cord is not ſoon bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Rev.</hi> 19.12. <hi>His eyes were as a flame of fire, and on his Head were many Crowns, and he hath a name given that no man knoweth but himſelf.</hi> In him is wonderful Majeſty, Dignity, and Excellencies incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by Creatures.<note place="margin">Cant. 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>This is my Beloved,</hi> may a Believer ſay, <hi>I am ſick of Love.</hi> God takes more kindly our Love to Chriſt, than he doth the Love of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: they ſee him in his Glory, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but love him; but we meet with many Oppoſitions and Temptations. For the Perſwaſion of the Love of Chriſt to our Souls, we ſhould preſs after it, thô (as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Divines of the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Suf. Brit.</note> that which many find by ſad Experience) this Satisfaction in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151471:26"/>is ſometimes <hi>vivida,</hi> ſometimes <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guida,</hi> and ſometimes as <hi>nulla;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>lively,</hi> ſometimes <hi>weak,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times even as <hi>none.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Remember, all the Saints in Heaven and Earth are Redeemed by Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. <hi>And (having made Peace through the Blood of his Croſs) by him, to Reconcile all things to himſelf by him; whether they be things in Earth, or things in Heaven.</hi> All the Saints that went to Glory before our Lord came in the fleſh, were bought by him: As a man may be ſaid to buy that, which he hath not yet paid for; Lands, Goods, Cloaths, whilſt there is a Satisfactory Promiſe made, and Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty given: So Chriſt bought them, in the Covenant between the Father and him, that he ſhould in the fulneſs of time, ſhed his blood for them.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Chriſt</hi> came into the World, the way to come to him was Repentance, and Faith; the Apoſtles preached it, and of theſe in the next Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151471:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Repentance and Faith.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>THE Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gives us a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium,</hi> or Abridgment of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Preaching Repenarnce and Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.22. Repentance ſheweth a man his ſin. When a Convert is in his Agonies and Pangs; in his throws and conflicts, then the heart, the once hard heart, falls a bleeding before God. Faith ſheweth a man his Saviour.<note place="margin">Acts 16.13.</note> We are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten call'd upon to believe in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why might it not be as well expreſt to believe in the Father, or in the Holy-Ghoſt, as in the Son? It is true, the Father, Son, and Holy-Ghoſt ſave us, but in a different way: The Father by ſending the Son; The Holy-Ghoſt as ſent from the Father and the Son, in the Hearts of Believers; but the Son by his Merits, by his Death. The Father contrived, the Spirit applyed, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> procured the Remedy. This Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151471:27"/>wounds, and Faith heals. By Faith we are ſaid to be juſtified,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God is revealed from Faith to Faith.</hi> Now when Chriſts Righteouſneſs is imputed unto us by Faith, it is not the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt as God; for that is his uncreated Righteouſneſs, and this eſſential Righteouſneſs cannot be communicated to us, and made our acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Righteouſneſs; and this is the Righteouſneſs of the Father and Spirit, as well as of the Son. And then Father and Spirit might be ſaid to juſtifie us, as well as the Son: But it is the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt the Mediatour, who is God man, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6. <hi>And this is his name whereby he ſhall be called, The Lord our Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p>Stay Reader ere thou goeſt any farther, if thou art an unconverted man, get, and cheriſh a few Reſolutions, to put in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice the few following Directions: Lift up thine eyes unto that God whoſe dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is not with fleſh, that he would thus incline thy heart: in hopes of this I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Go in ſecret, ſit down and conſider the great ſins of thy Heart and Life: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151471:28"/>time enough for this. Are you guilty of the horrible Sins of the Age? Try your ſelves by the Word, by the <hi>Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi> Can you not do this? will you do it?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Conſider theſe things, till you find your Hearts to ake, and Countenance to change. If you have ſuch Convictions as to ſay, O that I had not done theſe things! Could I live over my time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, things ſhould be otherwiſe: Thô ſuch Convictions may not be ſaving, yet they are too good to be thrown away. Strike, man, whilſt the Iron is hot.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Fall down on the Ground, pray to God for Pardon, and Acceptance through Chriſt: Say as <hi>Ezra,</hi> Chap. 9.6. <hi>O my God, I am aſhamed, and bluſh to lift up my face unto thee, My God: for our iniquities are increaſed over our Heads, and our Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs is grown up to the Heavens.</hi> Cry as the Leper,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord, if thou wilt thou canſt make me clean. Look to Jeſus</hi> typified by the <hi>bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 3.14, 15.</note> that thou mayeſt be heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Away to the minding of Secret, and Family Duties. Read the Scriptures, call on God, leſt the ſparks of Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions you have gotten, go out.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Converſe with them that Converſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151471:28"/>with God; ſay as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.115. <hi>Away from me you Evil-doers, for I will keep the Commandments of my God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.63.</note> I <hi>am a Companion of all them that fear thee, and of them that keep thy Precepts.</hi> Tell them your Caſe, beg their Prayers; hear their Inſtructions.</p>
                  <p>I have lain down a few plain Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Wherefore (I pray thee) O Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Let my counſel be acceptable in thy ſight, as an Ambaſſador of Chriſt:</hi> I pray thee <hi>as in Chriſts ſtead, as though God did beſeech thee, be thou Reconciled to God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> Will not this do? Then I adjure thee by that God that made thee, by that <hi>Jeſus</hi> that ſhall judge thee another day; Conſider thy ways. If any think a Death-bed-repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will ſerve thy turn, the famous <hi>Bolton</hi> ſaith, (that Oracle of his time) in his Directions for diſtreſſed Conſciences, That he could not get proof of any man Converted on a ſick Bed. I knew one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed three years upon ſick bed Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but at laſt grew more vile than ever. In ſome Reſpect we may bleſs God, that blaſteth ſuch Convictions: The World too much depends on them now, what would they do, if they ſaw them in any Perſons ſound and ſaving?<note place="margin">Mat. 20.7, 12.</note> If you ſay, ſome were called at the laſt hour; I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151471:29"/>anſwer, But none were called at the laſt minute. If a man in old age be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (which is very ſeldom) will it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, therefore a man on a Death-bed may be ſo. Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> (in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Sick-bed Repentance) tells us how we ſhould deal with ſuch. Gods example, ſaith he, muſt be our rule, <hi>Judg.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14, 16. to diſpenſe comfort by Degrees: When they cryed, God ſeems to deny Deliverance, and when they were greatly humbled, the Lord was grieved for them. He adviſeth Miniſters and others to ſhew ſuch men, the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mourning, and ſelf-indignation: If I be too forward to comfort them, I ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine them, ſaith he: I would to God they were of his mind, who are ſo forward to abſolve upon dry Confeſſions, and to Canonize in Funeral Sermons, to the great hardning of the Hearers. God will ſay by Conſcience on a ſick bed, <hi>What I have written, I have written,</hi> The Soul that Sins ſhall dye. Some are ready to ſay, If they mind theſe things now, they ſhall be out of their Wits. Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Souls! they have long ſince told the World by their Lives, that they were never well in their Wits. You know Phyſicians ſometimes ſay to their Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151471:29"/>Had I come timely, I might have cured you: If a Patient ſay, I will take no Phyſick, I will not be confined to my Chamber, I will eat and drink what I pleaſe; this is to ſay, I will not recover, I will dye: So to ſay in the heart, I will not follow Directions, is to ſay, I will be damned.</p>
                  <p>Remember, God that calls you, needs you not, <hi>Job</hi> 22.33. <hi>Is it any Pleaſure to the Almighty that thou art Righteous? or is it any gain to him, that thou makeſt thy way perfect?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let none deceive themſelves, and think they have repented and believed, when it is not ſo. They may ſay as <hi>Agag, Surely the bitterneſs of Death is paſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.32.33.</note> and <hi>yet be hewed before the Lord.</hi> O Bleſſed God! what a dreadful Surprizal will it be, in the time of Death to many great Profeſſours, that thought for twenty, thirty years or more, that they were in the Way to Heaven, and <hi>then,</hi> then find themſelves miſtaken; who find themſelves at the Gate of Hell, when they thought themſelves at the Gate of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Have you Convictions now? ſtifle them not, bring them before God, leſt he ſay of you, <hi>My Spirit ſhall no more strive with you, O man;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 6.3.</note> I take an everlaſting Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151471:30"/>of thee, ſeeing thou wilt be unholy, be unholy ſtill; and ſeeing thou wilt to Hell, to Hell ſhalt thou go. Do as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> cry and ſtrive long for the Bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.26. <hi>And he ſaid</hi> (that is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel) <hi>Let me go, for the day breaketh; and he ſaid, I will not let thee go until thou bleſs me.</hi> What if he had given over an hour or two after he began to wreſtle, or but an hour before he had the bleſſing, he had ſpoiled all: No, but he ſtrove <hi>the whole Night.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You that have repented, and believed, <hi>give Glory to the Lord</hi> your God. When God made a Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> he <hi>fell upon his face, Gen.</hi> 17.3. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> heard of their deliverance out of <hi>Egypt, they bowed down the head and worſhipped.</hi> He that believeth, feeleth he believeth; he knows the Acts of Faith phyſically conſidered, though not Morally: he hath the <hi>Faith of Adheſion,</hi> though it may be not <hi>of Evidence:</hi> he finds the lively wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of Faith, though he may not know whether they be of the right kind. But though our Safety depends upon the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Faith, yet our Comfort dependeth on our knowing that we have it. If you know it, ſay as <hi>David,</hi> when he had great things from God, he went and <hi>ſat in his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151471:30"/>houſe before the Lord,</hi> and ſaid, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.20. <hi>And what can David ſay more unto thee? for thou Lord God knoweſt thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi> Or as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> 
                     <hi>What ſhall we ſay to theſe things?</hi> What indeed! Now may you rejoyce, <hi>that inſtead of the Thorn is come up the Fir-tree, and inſtead of the Brier is come up the Myrtle-tree,</hi> Iſa. 55.13. Inſtead of Sin in the heart, Grace now grows, and inſtead of abominable practices in the life, there are now good works.</p>
                  <p>They that have repented, and believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhould endeavour the Converſion, and Confirmation of many in the Faith, as they did, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. that by them, <hi>may be added unto the Church, ſuch as ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> But of this in the Following Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Reproof and Counſel.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>WHO can ſufficiently bewail the neglect, or ſlight performing of this Duty by moſt good men? though
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151471:31"/>the bleſſing that followeth the ſerious practiſing of it by ſome, be very great. How many times have we been by Land, by Water a long time with many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and never drop one Word ſuitable to their Condition! Nay, ſometimes the Spirit hath ſpoken to our Conſciences, what once it did to <hi>Philip</hi> concerning the <hi>Eunuch, Go join thy ſelf to him, Act.</hi> 8.29. yet Shame, want of Courage, Lazineſs hath kept from it. All ſorts of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may be uſeful this way. We read, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.24. <hi>Priſcilla</hi> a Woman, taught <hi>Apollos</hi> a man, <hi>an eloquent man, a man mighty in the Scriptures, the Way of God more perfectly,</hi> verſ. 26. Biſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted when eleven years old, by a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.) would as ſoon preach at the Requeſt of a poor Woman, as of a Magiſtrate; and he delighted more to converſe with poor weak Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, than with many Learned men. I may truly ſay to many Women, on whoſe Souls the Image of God hath been drawn in a lively manner, what <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abigal,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.32, 33. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, which ſent thee this day to meet me, and bleſſed be thy Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi> It is the Property of a proud <hi>Phariſee,</hi> not of a humble Chriſtian, to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151471:31"/>contemn Reproof and Counſel from an inferiour, or a mean Perſon; <hi>John</hi> 9.34. The Phariſees could not bear a few plain, pious conſiderations from a poor blind man, but ſaid to him, <hi>Thou waſt altogether born in Sin, and wilt thou Teach us? and they caſt him out: Thou, us. Thou</hi> an illeterate man, as blind in thy Soul, as once in thy Body: <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> great men, great Profeſſours. Let the Counſel be never ſo good, it will not take with many wiſe fools, if it come from a plain man.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>F. P.</hi> Coun. of Trent.</note> 
                     <hi>Mattheo Longi</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Saltzburge,</hi> after he read the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine Confeſſion</hi> of Faith, by the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Zuinglians</hi> in <hi>Zuric,</hi> he told every one, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Maſs was honeſt, and the liberty of meats convenient, and the requeſt juſt, to be disburthened of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Commandments of men; but that <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> a poor Monk, ſhould Reform, was not to be endured.</p>
                  <p>God is ſo well pleaſed with this work of turning Souls to Righteouſneſs, that the Bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had his name changed from <hi>Saul,</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi> becauſe he was the inſtrument of Converting a famous man, call'd <hi>Paul;</hi> Acts 13.9. <hi>Then Saul who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is called Paul;</hi> There is the change of his name, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. <hi>Paulus, a prudent man,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151471:32"/>a Deputy, called for Barnabas and Saul to hear the Word of God.</hi> So one ſayes of this Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Platina</hi> de vita Pon. tif.</note> 
                     <hi>A Paulo proconſule Cypri, nomen accepit, quem praedicatione ſua ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem redegerat.</hi> What care then ſhould Parents take of the Souls of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Maſters of their Servants, Friends of one another? For Children, it is true, whilſt they are Infants they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be inſtructed, but may be pray'd for: for as Sin and miſery comes on them, and they not ſenſible of it, ſo may Gods Grace and Mercy: they are Members of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Subjects of a King, and yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand this: So they may be Members of the Body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Subjects of the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and have no knowledg of this. They may have great Eſtates, and the benefit of Rents, and yet know not what an Eſtate is, or Rents are. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed they ſhould be as they grow up, that they may ſay of their Parents as <hi>Solomon</hi> of his, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>I was my Fathers Son, tender and onely beloved in the ſight of my Mother.</hi> He <hi>taught me alſo, and ſaid unto me, Let thy heart retain my words. Keep my Commandements and live.</hi> Happy are thoſe children, that can ſay when their Parents are dead: I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what my Father and Mother now in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151471:32"/>Glory, ſaid to me; how they inſtructed me. In the ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. we read of the good effects of this duty: <hi>When I call to mind the unfeigned Faith that is in thee, which firſt dwelt in thy Grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lois, and thy Mother Eunice, and I am perſwaded that it is in thee alſo.</hi> What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort may good Parents take in good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren! <hi>Socrates Scholaſticus</hi> ſays of <hi>Leoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> the father of <hi>Origen,</hi> that when his Son was aſleep, he would ſometimes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his breaſt, and kiſs it with a kind of veneration, knowing his Son was a Temple for the Holy Ghoſt to dwell in: <hi>Leonides</hi> was wont, when <hi>Origen</hi> was very young, to teach him ſome Aphoriſms, and Sentences in Chriſtianity every day, which made ſuch a deep impreſſion upon him, that he was ſoon called <hi>Senilis Puer,</hi> the Old Boy; <hi>Vir magnus ab Infantia,</hi> A great man from his Childhood: Young he was in years onely, but old in Knowledg and Grace. When <hi>Bathſheba</hi> had a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from King <hi>David,</hi> that <hi>Solomon</hi> her Son ſhould be King after him, it is ſaid, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.31. <hi>That ſhe bowed her face to the earth, and did reverence to the King, and ſaid, Let my Lord King David live for ever.</hi> Adore the Lord God if he hath made your Children, by his Grace, Heirs of <hi>the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151471:33"/>Kingdom that cannot be ſhaken.</hi> Give me leave, by the way, to bewail the great and common ſin found among us, That many children are ſooner taught what <hi>Jupiter, Mars,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Pagan Gods</hi> were, than what Father, Son, and Spirit is. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, when he was young,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chron. 34.3.</note> 
                     <hi>enquired after the God of David his Father;</hi> but many now when young, after Heathen Gods. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> of old complained of this,<note place="margin">Aug. Confeſ. <hi>lib. 6.</hi>
                     </note> of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Schools, <hi>Joves</hi> Thundering, and Adulteries, and for giving an account of ſuch things, ſaith he, <hi>Et ob hoc bonae ſpei puer appellabar,</hi> I was called a hopeful Lad. <hi>Luther</hi> alſo complained, that our Schools were more Pagan, than Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. I referr the unſatisfied Reader to <hi>Paſors</hi> Preface to his <hi>Lexicon;</hi> he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his golden verſes, ſo much eſteemed of (and I fear accounted more golden by too many, than our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Sayings on the Mount) how they begin;</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>— <hi>Honour the Immortal Gods,</hi> &amp;c. And (as I have obſerved) worſe after. I knew an Aged Famous Schoolmaſter, that after he had kept School about fifty years, ſaid, with a very ſad countenance, That it was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151471:33"/>a great trouble to him, that he had ſpent ſo much time in reading <hi>Pagan</hi> Authors to his Scholars; and wiſht it were cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary, to read ſuch a Book as <hi>Duports</hi> Greek Verſes upon <hi>Job,</hi> rather than <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> and ſuch Books. I beſeech School-maſters, if they muſt read ſuch Authors, do as they do that eat <hi>Muſhromes,</hi> or ſuch dangerous meats, uſe ſtrong Correctives. Shew Youth the vanity of the Pagan Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the excellency of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion: Perſwade them above all things, to be acquainted with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, <hi>which alone can make them wiſe to Salvation,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15. when many vain books make many wiſe to Damnation. If Children die, what doth it ſignifie to ſay they were ingenious, if they be graceleſs? will Ingenuity ſave them? They are as <hi>Thales Mileſius,</hi> that was gazing on the Stars, minding their magnitude, ſituation, and influences, when he ſhould have been minding his way, and ſo fell into the water, and was drowned. I pray God put it in the hearts of a wiſe Parliament, to purge our Schools; that inſtead of learning vain Fictions, and filthy ſtories, they may be acquainted with the VVord of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151471:34"/>God, with Books containing Grave Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: And learn in <hi>Proſe</hi> or <hi>Verſe,</hi> the Hiſtories of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> the chief Paſſages in their Reigns, and ſome Maxims in Law, and things that may make them truly wiſe, and uſeful in the world. I know I ſhall offend not a few in thus writing: But let ſuch remember my Authors before named, <hi>Auſtin, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Paſor,</hi> and others that I might name, and if I muſt have a Reprimand, I am glad that I have ſuch good company. It is ſtoried of the old <hi>Waldenſes</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in the dark times of Popery,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>R.</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> they ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed their Children in the great things of God, that ſome Popiſh Doctors ſaid, that they learned more of the Doctrine of Salvation, by talking with thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, than they did by the Diſputations of great men. There is another fault among us to be condemned, the early and unneceſſary ſending of young men beyond Sea, to ſee Countreys, ſpeak Languages, before they have ſtudied the grounds of our Religion, and ſo are infected with Popery, or Atheiſm. I deſire ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſend their Children away, or the Children before they go, to read Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Hall</hi> his <hi>Quo vadis,</hi> a Book to which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151471:34"/>little can be added: And then I hope; they may be willing to ſtay at home.</p>
                  <p>How ſad is it in moſt houſes, where the fear of God is not! Of which it may be ſaid, what is ſaid of <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 18.2. that they are <hi>a Habitation of Devils, and the hold of every foul Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> and the cage of every unclean and hateful Bird;</hi> ſo many wicked perſons, and ſo much wickedneſs is in them, that the ſerious Chriſtian may ſometimes ſay in the beholding of it, what <hi>Job</hi> ſaid in another caſe, <hi>O that my grief were thorougly weighed, and that my ſorrow were laid in the ballance, for then would it be heavier than the ſand of the Sea!</hi> That there is ſo much Lying, Prophaning the Name of God, and ſo much of unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury, rotten communications in moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and among Children, that when they are men and women, theſe things become common to them: That if it be then asked, what <hi>Chriſt</hi> asked the Father about his Childs diſeaſe, <hi>how long ago this happened to them;</hi> the ſame anſwer may be given, <hi>even from a Child,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Mark,</hi> 9.21. I now come to a few Directions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Cry to God for Bowels of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion toward Souls, and for Dexterity
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151471:35"/>in this work of Reproving and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that you may ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 9.1, 2, 3. <hi>I ſay the Truth in Chriſt, I lye not, my Conſcience alſo bearing me Witneſs in the Holy Ghoſt, that I have great heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and continual Sorrow in my Heart, for I could wiſh that my ſelf were accurſed from Chriſt, for my Brethren, my Kinſmen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh.</hi> As if he had ſaid, I could almoſt be willing to periſh for their ſakes: ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119.158. <hi>I beheld the Tranſgreſſors, and was grieved, becauſe they kept not thy Word.</hi> You Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, that are ſo tender of the Bodies of your Children, be much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for their Souls. You that deſire great Eſtates for them, much more deſire Heaven for them. How many mind their Oxen, Sheep, and Swine, more than the Souls of their Children? <hi>Sauls</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Kiſh,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Gave over caring for the Aſſes, ſaying, What ſhall I do for my Son?</hi> So, be leſs concerned about the things of the World, and ſay, What ſhall I do for the Souls of my Children? that it may be ſaid, of you, as in <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.20. <hi>The Mouth of the Righteous is as choice Silver;</hi> when you ſpeak with tender Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Compaſſion, <hi>It is not you that ſpeak, but the Spirit of your Father that ſpeaketh
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151471:35"/>in you, Mat.</hi> 10.20. When God bad <hi>Moſes to ſpeak to Pharaoh,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected want of Eloquence, ſaid God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Now therefore go and I will be thy mouth, and I will teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay:</hi> That you may by your good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel overcome Satan, as <hi>David,</hi> by playing with his Muſical Inſtrument, made the evil Spirit to depart from <hi>Saul.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.23.</note> I know for ſome audacious Sinners, it is better to be ſilent, than reprove. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his command was prudent, when <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> Blaſphemed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.21. <hi>But the People held their peace, and anſwered him not a Word; for the Kings Commandment was, ſaying, Anſwer him not.</hi> Let Prayer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the work of Exhorting;<note place="margin">Neh. 2.4.</note> ſtand before the man, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> before the King and Queen, praying to the God of Heaven to direct you what you ſhall ſay. Pray, Lord, let my words <hi>adminiſter Grace to the Hearers, Epheſ.</hi> 4.29. Ask ſome that are under you, after the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Chapter, or hearing of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, what <hi>Chriſt</hi> asked his Diſciples, Mat. 13.51. <hi>Have ye understood all thoſe things?</hi> Heal their Ignorance, direct their Souls.</p>
                  <p>We ſee Afflictions do many times ſtir Chriſtians up to this Work, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151471:36"/>them for it: <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of great Troubles he endured; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4. <hi>But in all things approving our ſelves as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, in much Patience, in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, in Neceſſities, in Diſtreſſes.</hi> Verſ. 9.10. <hi>As unknown, and yet well-known; as dying, and behold we live; as chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not killed; as ſorrowful, yet always Rejoycing; as poor, yet making many rich; as having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> What did this bleſſed Apoſtle get by all? <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>O ye Corinthians, our Mouth is open unto you, our Heart is enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> He got a Heart to pity Souls, and a Tongue to Counſel them. <hi>There is Gold, and a multitude of Rubies, but the Lips of Knowledge are precious Jewels,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 20.15. Good Counſel given, is better than the giving of Gold. Whilſt you are muſing, the fire may kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and then you ſpeak with your Tongue. If you cannot ſpeak to ſome, write to them; Letters will not bluſh, if Faces do.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Have an eye upon the Sins they are moſt addicted to, and Reprove for them; and on the Duties they are moſt averſe from, and perſwade to them. It is not enough that the Words ſpoken by you be good, but they muſt be ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151471:36"/>Words. Some are apt to uſe the Name of God irreverently in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications: Nay, many great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, I am aſhamed to mention it. It hath been a comfortable Conſideration to me many a time, that when I dye, I ſhall be tormented with hearing the Name of God irreverently uſed,<note place="margin">☜</note> no more. Would to God the third Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment <hi>(Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain)</hi> were often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of men. Tell ſuch men, that they ought to <hi>fear that great and terrible Name, the Lord thy God:</hi> That they have Reaſon to adore him, that he will give us leave to uſe his Name at any time, and therefore we ſhould not take it in vain: whether theuſing in common Diſcourſe the Word <hi>Faith,</hi> be Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I know the great <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Saunder.</hi> de juro mento.</note> (that <hi>per fidem</hi> though from the manner of ſome Nations, and intention of ſome Speakers, it may, be an Oath) yet he ſaith, <hi>Non eſt ex vi Verborum,</hi> becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>Fides Humana non eſt res Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra, but civilis;</hi> and in thoſe words we call not God a Witneſs, and therefore is <hi>Aſſeveratio tantum, aut ad plurimum Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio:</hi> And ſo he adds, that <hi>per fidem,</hi> is the ſame with <hi>Ex animo loquor, Pignero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidem
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151471:37"/>meam, ſi rem ita ſe non habere, aut ſi ſciens fallo, nulla mihi in poſterum fides ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beatur.</hi> So he. If you ask, Is it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thus to uſe the Word <hi>Faith?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I am ſure it is not unlawful to let it alone: it is not a thing of good report to uſe, and the more ſerious decline it. Are they addicted to Lying, Scoffing at Religion? Shew them the evil nature, and conſequents of theſe things. If they ſlight Prayer, the Holy Scriptures, Alms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, perſwade to them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Be not ſoon diſcouraged, becauſe of the Ignorance or Backwardneſs of them with whom you deal: God may in time work on them. Are they ignorant? ſpeak to them of Chriſt, and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, and of the way of Sinners coming to God through a Mediatour; ſhew them kindneſs, and ſeek to make their lives comfortable as much as you can, that you may the better win them. If any ſay, We are ignorant our ſelves, and how can we inſtruct others? This is the way to get knowledge. You know that God made the world: That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is a glorious Redeemer: That all men are haſtning to Eternity. Come man, come on, thou knoweſt enough to fall on the practice of this duty; ſpeak
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151471:37"/>to vain ſpirits of theſe things. Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> in his Account of the Progreſs of the Goſpel in <hi>New-England,</hi> written in the year 43. ſpeaks of one <hi>Hiacoomes,</hi> a plain, ignorant, but yet pious and ſerious man; he converted one <hi>Towanquetick</hi> a plain <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> and this <hi>Towanquetick</hi> was the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of the converſion of about a hundred <hi>Indians</hi> in a little time. If o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay, We are ignorant, after all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and therefore are diſcouraged; let ſuch often call to mind what they hear, and time may make an impreſſion. I have read of <hi>Hilarius Pictavienſes</hi> a famous man of <hi>France,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hanmore's View of Antiqu.</note> finding that little that he read was remembred by him, threw away his Books: One day paſſing by a Well, he ſaw, that by frequent drawing up of the Bucket, the rope had made a deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on the Stones; he thought that by frequent conſideration, and meditation, the things he heard and read might make a deep impreſſion on him; he fell cloſely to his work, and proved a famous man.</p>
                  <p>You that are ungodly, and hear not your Inſtructors, you diſcourage them in their work, that they are ready to ſay as <hi>Jeremiah, Then I ſaid, I will not make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, nor ſpeak any more in his name.</hi> But zeal for God, and love to Souls,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151471:38"/>makes them at laſt to come to themſelves; and add as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">Jer. 20.9.</note> 
                     <hi>But his word was in my heart, as a burning fire ſhut up in my bones, and I was weary of forbearing, and I could not ſtay.</hi> How many ſerious Souls have experienced this!<note place="margin">The Life of Mr. <hi>Janeway.</hi>
                     </note> When Mr. <hi>Janeway</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verheard ſome unſavoury diſcourſe, in a room nigh to him, he wrote down their diſcourſe, and asked them, after he had read what they ſaid, whether they were willing to hear of ſuch diſcourſe another day. Many men by their evil diſcourſe, poyſon many hearers, as the <hi>Baſilisk</hi> doth men,<note place="margin">Morney's Reſolver.</note> not by looking on them (according to the vulgar error) but by Poyſon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of the mouth. Children, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to your Parents, that prerſwade you to mind your Souls; grieve them not by your folly. Let good men hearken to Reproof from their Brethren, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did from <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> from <hi>Paul.</hi> When <hi>Luther</hi> reproved <hi>Bullinger,</hi> for ſome errors he had about the Word of God, <hi>Bullinger</hi> came forth before all the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and fell at the feet of <hi>Luther,</hi> and ſaid, Bleſſed be the day wherein I ſaw this gracious face, and had theſe reproofs. Let good men counſel then their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Servants, and Friends. It is ſad, that ſuch ſhould ſay, My Father, my
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151471:38"/>Maſter, my Friend, that is a great Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Religion, and with whom I am on all occaſions, by day, by night, never was the man that asked me, what I thought of my preſent, or eternal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; never aked me whether I thought I was converted, or ſhould be ſaved. Yet ſet cloſely to the work, and let it proſper in thy hands, that <hi>you may ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and as the Stars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 12.3. But becauſe the Scripture inſtructs us, and contains the things about which we muſt inſtruct others, I ſhall next ſpeak of them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Holy Scriptures.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>GODS Works declare, that he <hi>is;</hi> but his Word only declares <hi>what</hi> he is, and how he may be known and ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If we ſee a Ship under Sail, going towards its Port, we aſcribe not this to the wood the Ship is made of, but to the skill of the Mariners, whether they be ſeen by us or not. If I ſee an Arrow run
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151471:39"/>to the Mark, I know it is ſhot off by a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hand, whether I ſee that hand or not. The Sun, that great and glorious light, knoweth its riſing, progreſs, and going down, and acts like an intelligent, ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal being, which ſhews it is guided by a wiſe God. As for Gods Providences, which make ſome doubt his being, Sir <hi>W. R.</hi> in his Hiſtory of the World, <hi>Chap. Of Predeſtination,</hi> hath this ſaying of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> (which he ſaid was of great uſe to him) <hi>Qui in Dei factis rationem non videt, infirmitatem ſuam conſideret, et cur non videt rationem videat.</hi> He that cannot ſee a reaſon in ſome of Gods Works, let him conſider his weakneſs, and then he will ſee the reaſon why he ſees no reaſon. I conclude, That the reaſon why many would hope they ſhall die like Beaſts, is, that they deſire to live like ſuch. Now the Scriptures contain a declaration of the Mind and Will of this God. I will not determine how many Chapters every one ſhould read, every day, any more than how much meat every one ſhould eat every day. Three Chapters a day (the uſual direction) are too many for ſome, and (ſometimes) too few for others. I am not perſwading to much reading, but ſerious reading: And for young Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151471:39"/>I think it proper, that they be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the chief places in Scripture, and well to underſtand them, before they read the Bible in order. The reading of Scripture with a good Comment, is of great uſe to ſome perſons, and Families: I know none for ſhortneſs, and plaineſs, like to <hi>Biſhop Halls Paraphraſe on the Bible.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Come to the Scriptures, as thoſe that know a Divine Authority ſtamped upon them. It is Gods Book, read it as ſuch: It teacheth you the two things <hi>Auſtin</hi> would often pray for; <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam te, ut cognoſcam me;</hi> That I may know Thee, that I may know my ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Beg the aſſiſtance of the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in reading the Scriptures, that the Pen-men had in penning them. A Dial is nothing, unleſs the Sun ſhine on it: The Scriptures are nothing, unleſs the Spirit illuminate our Underſtandings. If you ſay, what need then of Scriptures? You may as well ſay, what need then of a Dial? The Spirit will make you humble. and let you ſee your own Folly, that the more you know, the leſs you know.<note place="margin">Weems Chriſt. Syn.</note> In <hi>Athens</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> the Students were the firſt year called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, wiſe men; the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151471:40"/>next year <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Lovers of wiſe men; but ever after <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Fools; the more they knew, the more ſenſible they were of their Ignorance.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whatever Objections you have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture, be not ſatisfyed till you have ſilenced them. To confirm your Faith, remember what is ſaid of Chriſt's Reſurrection: Had the <hi>Jews</hi> been able to ſhew the dead Body of Chriſt after the three dayes, they had overthrown the Goſpel. Remember <hi>Pauls</hi> Converſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. who left a life of eaſe, for one of affliction. <hi>Judas</hi> his betraying Chriſt, proves that he knew Chriſt to be no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver: He had not hanged himſelf to have accuſed Chriſt, had he not known his Miracles were real; many of them were not done in a Corner, the place named, the Street, and done before many people. The Diſciples converſed with Chriſt forty dayes after his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſaw him aſcend into Heaven. They preached this to the world, when they knew this Doctrine would coſt them their Lives, and it was never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that in all their torments that any one of them confeſſed a Cheat,<note place="margin">Leviath. Chriſt. Pol.</note> but rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that they were going to that Chriſt whom they had thus ſeen and preached.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151471:40"/>Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> though he is pleaſed to tell us, that the Scriptures were in the hands of the Eccleſiaſticks, for about three hundred years after the Apoſtles, (he had done well to have proved it as well as ſaid it,) yet ſaith, <hi>he believed the Scriptures were not corrupted by them.</hi> If there ſeem to be any Coutradictions in Scripture (ſaith <hi>Morney</hi>) we ſhould do with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as Scholars with Claſſical Authors: If they meet with a hard Sentence, they do not preſently throw away the Book,<note place="margin">Morney, de ver. Chriſt. Rel.</note> but turn it this way, and that way, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſay, the Author wrote not ſenſe, or true Latine, or Greek: <hi>Diſcipulus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptorem, praeceptor ignorantiam accuſat:</hi> The Scholar blames the Maſter, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter his Ignorance, but neither blame the Author. Many paſſages in Scripture Hiſtory we cannot eaſily reconcile, for want of knowing ſome Occurrences in thoſe times: I have in this caſe, often made uſe of ſuch a Meditation as this (which one night came into my thoughts:) If two men writing the Hiſtory of the Reign of our preſent King, one ſhould write, that this year was the thirty fifth year of his Reign; and the other ſhould write, that this was the twenty third year of his Reign: A Stranger, or ſome Beyond
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151471:41"/>Sea would wonder at this different ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and would cry out, that there was a notorious Contradiction in theſe two Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians: but we that know how Affairs have been in <hi>England,</hi> know that both wrote true: This is the <hi>35th</hi> year of his Reign, if we conſider how long he hath Reigned <hi>de jure,</hi> upon the death of his Father; this is the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> year of his Reign, if we reckon how long he hath Reigned <hi>de facto,</hi> or ſince his retnrn. A young Grammarian, might quarrel with his Grammar, when he read of a Singular Number, when Number muſt be at leaſt of two: Of a Conjunction Disjunctive, and cry, O Horrible Contradiction in Terms! when there is a conjunction of words, where there is a Disjunction of Senſe.</p>
                  <p>If any ſay, But a great part of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we underſtand not. I anſwer, And a great part of Scripture you do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: VVhat can be more plain than thoſe Scriptures againſt Sin and for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs? I have heard of an Unchaſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that was objecting the obſcurity of the Scripture, and that ſhe could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it: <hi>How Madam</hi> (replyed one) <hi>what more plain than this? Thou ſhalt not Commit Adultery.</hi> Conſider again, what
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151471:41"/>did the Eunuch underſtand? <hi>Acts</hi> 8.30. God helped him ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> to him, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt?</hi> A good queſtion, <hi>How can I,</hi> (ſaid he:) And <hi>Philip</hi> inſtructed him: Here all met, that ſome would part; Here was Scripture, for he read ſome of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> his Propheſie. Here was the Spirit that bad <hi>Philip</hi> go to him; Here was the Preacher, for <hi>Philip</hi> expounds all to him. Who throws away a letter of great concern, becauſe he cannot read all, nor underſtand all? he reads it the oftner, takes the more pains, calls for help, and glad to underſtand moſt of it, when he cannot underſtand all. If any plead, We cannot read: A good Woman (in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time) that could not read, got a new Teſtament, went from houſe to houſe, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red others to read to her, and ſoon got much knowledge: Knowledge doth not get into the Soul by the Eye onely, but by the Ear. Many under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the myſteries of their Trades, that never read Books about them: Many can tell what news is going, that never look into <hi>Gazets,</hi> or <hi>News-letters,</hi> by hearing and conſidering. <hi>I have</hi> (ſaith God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.12.) <hi>written to them
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151471:42"/>the great things of my Law, but they were counted as a ſtrange thing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If any ſay, I want time. Can you find time to eat, to ſleep, and not to look into the Word of God? Some can find time to read vain books, that can find none to read Scripture: Tho' ſuch are as <hi>Politianus,</hi> that left reading the Scripture,<note place="margin">Morney de ver. Rel. Chriſt.</note> and ſtudied and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about ſuch queſtions as theſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhould write <hi>Carthaginenſes,</hi> or <hi>Carthaginienſes,</hi> &amp;c. As inſignificant are all other Studies, when men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the Word of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If you find Convictions from Gods Word, loſe them not as you have too often done; <hi>Cain,</hi> when terrified in his mind, built Cities: <hi>Saul</hi> called for Muſick; ſo ſome run to their profits, and pleaſures. If a man had great Treaſure about him, and came by a dangerous way where many were rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and he himſelf had ſome time been robbed, how would he fear? As the Lord liveth, thou art the man: Thou haſt been many times richly laden with good convictions, affections, and purpoſes gotten from the Word of God; the Cares and Temptations of the world have robbed thee, and feek to do it again.</p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:151471:42"/>
                  <p n="5">5. Remember, You that are Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, what Encouragement they had in Scripture, you have; and by them,<note place="margin">Joſh. 1.5. Heb. 13.5.</note> God directeth and comforteth you; <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6. where he ſpeaks of <hi>Jacob, Yea, he had Power over the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, and prevailed; he wept and made ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication unto him: he found him in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel, and there he ſpake with us;—There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore turn thou to thy God: Keep mercy and Judgment, wait on thy God continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> God by giving <hi>Jacob</hi> the bleſſing, ſpeaks to us to wait on God. But to the Scripture, we muſt add Prayer: But of that in the next Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>THE great Benefit and Comfort of Prayer, we read of often in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and the People of God find of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by experience. Family Prayer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.2</note> and Secret Prayer,<note place="margin">Acts 10.2.</note> have been minded by the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151471:43"/>Saints of Old. In Secret Prayer, it is good to ſtop ſometimes after ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, Petitions and Praiſes, that the heart may be more deeply affected with them. Never did any Believer pray in vain, though ſometimes it may ſeem long before God anſwer. When Corn is ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, Rain comes, Snow comes, Proſt comes, and all ſeems to be loſt, but ſtay till the time of Harveſt, and there is a good Crop; ſo after Prayer Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come, ſad Providences come, and yet at laſt all is well. When a Child of God is in Prayer, he is not weary of God, nor of the duty; but weary of himſelf, and the corruption of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; of Satan and his Temptations; but ſtill may ſay, <hi>How good is it to draw nigh to God!</hi> In Secret Prayer, if unſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thoughts come, of men or buſineſs, pray about thoſe things as occaſion may be, ſo will ye catch the Devil in his own craft. He is not ſo wiſe, but he may be outwitted: He hath helped me by his Temptations to matter of Prayer thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of times, againſt his Will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>Directions in anſwer to a Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>Q. <hi>But what if I have no heart to the work?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Pray obedientially, when you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151471:43"/>pray comfortably. God calls for Prayer, wait on him in the face of all diſcouragements. Obedience will make an unpleaſant work pleaſant.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Remember, that diſcompoſure may quickly end in enlargement. <hi>Abraham</hi> found his Ram on the Mount,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.13.</note> and that in the Thickets: So many find their hearts in Prayer (not before) and that in the midſt of violent Temptations.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Remember, that many Prayers, we reckon ſome of the worſt, God accounts as ſome of our beſt Prayers; Great are the rewards for what ſome think to be dead Prayers. We reckon the goodneſs of Prayer by compoſure of thoughts, by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but God by ſelf-loathing, and ſeeing nothing in our ſelves and duties, but all in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Let us cry earneſtly to our God. Pagans have cryed aloud to their Gods, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.26. <hi>They cut themſelves, and leapt upon the Altars which they made.</hi> If any ſay, I know not how to pray in Secret, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet did it, I know not what to ſay: Go to God and ſay ſo. It is a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>Lord here I am come, I would pray, but know not what to ſay.</hi> It may be given you in that hour, what to confeſs, and pray for, and that with great melting of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151471:44"/>heart. Ask the Experience of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God: Love them, but of that in the following Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Love to Mankind.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LEt Brotherly Love continue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13.1.</note> is in many mens mouths, but in few mens hearts. If we enquire <hi>who is our Brother?</hi> Not the man nearly related, or the man of the ſame perſwaſion, or opinion one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but chiefly all of the Houſhold of Faith. How many men of ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are as <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that have no dealing one with another! We muſt love the Saints, as rich, ſo poor ones; ignorant as well as learned; the weak as well as the ſtrong. We muſt love the ungodly, yea our Enemies: Love is to be ſhewn in forgiving injuries, in ſupplying neceſſities: If any hate us, we muſt love them; if they deferve bad of us, they (and we alſo) deferve worſe of God,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151471:44"/>yet God feedeth them, cloatheth them,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> and ſhews them mercy. If God will uſe them as his Rod to chaſtiſe us, we muſt be content. Who knows what wrath will do, or where it will end? It is ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried of Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> that he ſo hated Pope <hi>Formoſus,</hi> that he cauſed his Body to be taken out of the Grave, and cut off thoſe Fingers that had bleſſed the Clergy, and ſo made void all his Canons, and Ordinances: And he that came after him took meaſures ſomewhat like, ſo that at laſt, ſaith <hi>Platina, Nihil enim aliud, hi Pontifices cogitabant, quam &amp; nomen &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Majorum ſuorum extinguere;</hi> and yet all theſe men were Infallible all the while. Let Husbands and Wives reſolve, that their contentions ſhall not eaſily take Air, or be ſeen by them in the Family; <hi>They are one Body,</hi> and contentions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, are as if there ſhould be a fight between the Members of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; As if the mouth ſhould bite the hand, and the hand ſtrike the mouth. A wrathful temper is commonly gotten by converſing with angry men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Wiſe man, <hi>Make no friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with an angry man; and with a furious man thou ſhalt not go; lest thou learn his wayes, and get a ſnare to thy Soul,</hi> Prov.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151471:45"/>22.24, 25. Beware of men of keen Spirits. That man will never live com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, that hath not learned to ſlight what others think, and ſay of him; that liveth not in the frequent conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other mens vertues, and his own defects: <hi>Epictetus</hi> in the 48 Chap. of his Morals, ſaith; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>If any man tell you, that ſuch a man ſpoke againſt you, do not ſo much ſtand in vindication of your ſelf, as ingenuouſly to confeſs; that if that man had known the whole courſe of your life, he had charged you with more faults.</hi> Few men are ſo humble, as to ſay, <hi>The fault was mine,</hi> though they certainly know it is ſo.</p>
                  <p>Kindneſs and Love is ſhewn, as in forgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing injuries, ſo in ſupplying neceſſities. Here we may bewail the diſparity, that is between many poor mens pains, and their wages. Though common wages be paid, yet the pay is according to cuſtome more than deſert; <hi>Etiamſi stipendia uſitata prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentur</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ames de Conſci.</hi>) <hi>conſuetudini, magis quam ſufficientiae ſatisfaciunt.</hi> Then for Charity to the poor; No man that hath loved the world better than his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151471:45"/>or Chriſt in his Members,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.35.</note> ſhall be found at the right hand of Jeſus in the great day. The ſaying of <hi>Salvian, ad Eccleſiam Catholicam,</hi> hath been of great uſe to me, times without number; <hi>Opes, quas habes in hoc mundo temporarias, bene utendo facies ſempiternas; Charity makes Temporal Riches to be Eternal:</hi> We have the benefit of them for ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Remember, what God Commands you to give to the poor, that you have no right to; and it is theft to detain it, as may be made clear by this plain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon: One man, by a Carrier ſends ſo much money, or goods to another; if that Carrier keep all, becauſe all came to his hands, he is a Thief, and is dealt with as ſuch. God hath ſent ſo much to the diſtreſſed by you, if you give not, you wrong them.</p>
                  <p>Obj. <hi>God hath ſent ſo much, ſome may ſay, How much?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ask God by Prayer, Scripture by reading, Conſcience by Conſideration: <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.97. <hi>With-hold not good from him, to whom it is due.</hi> Luke 16.12. <hi>If ye have been unfaithful in that which is another mans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Conclude on it, if the poor die for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151471:46"/>want of what we are bound to give them, we are Manſlayers, and Murtherers before God. He that ſees a man in the water, and will not help him out when he can with eaſe, he is as really guilty of his death, as if he had thrown him in. How many poor men, good men have periſhed for want of their right! If God ſhould ſay to ſome great men, rich men, as he did to <hi>Cain, Where is Abel thy Brother?</hi> So where is the poor man, thy Brother? It may be he would anſwer as he, <hi>Am I my Brothers Keeper?</hi> But the ſame reply ſhall be made by the Lord, <hi>What haſt thou done? The Voice of thy Brothers Blood cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto me from the ground, and now thou art Curſed,</hi> Gen. 4.9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Remember what an honour it is to be Gods Almoner. What if God in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had named you, as <hi>Joſiah</hi> by name, and call'd on you to the work, would you not chearfully have ſet about the work? How did <hi>Job</hi> rejoyce in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this duty! <hi>Job</hi> 29.13, 14, 15, 16. He <hi>cauſed the Widows heart to ſing:</hi> That his <hi>Judgment was a Robe, and a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade:</hi> That he <hi>was eyes to the Blind, and feet to the lame, and a Father to the Poor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some object, <hi>Times are hard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, Mens Hearts are ſo.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:151471:46"/>
                  <p>Obj. <hi>Money is ſcarce.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> How is it then you have ſo much to lay out in unneceſſary Attire; Diſhes at your Tables; in Pleaſures? How comes ſo much to be ſpent in Alehouſes and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns? This, O vain man, is but a Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaf to cover thy nakedneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> Others do plead, <hi>Few of the great Profeſſors of Religion do mind this work.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, But from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it was not ſo. The <hi>Jews</hi> under the Old Teſtament did much, Chriſtians in <hi>Pauls</hi> time did much. Do not what <hi>moſt</hi> Profeſſors do; but what the <hi>beſt</hi> do. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in our time have acted worthily: The famous Mr. <hi>Gouge</hi> (now in Glory) he ſet up an Hundred and fifty Schools in <hi>Wales,</hi> and went (at leaſt) once a year to viſit them, gave away many Bibles, and Catechiſms, and took great pains in inſtructing Children in the Principles of Religion, and would often ſay; That he had two Livings, the one in <hi>Wales,</hi> the other in <hi>Chriſt-Church Hoſpital</hi> in <hi>London</hi> (where he had done much good) that he would not part with for a world. My never to be forgotten Friend, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>Fairclougb</hi> of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> his Purſe was alwayes open for pious uſes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for educating young men in order to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151471:47"/>the Miniſtry. I might ſay much of Mr. <hi>Henry Stubbes</hi> my Father-in-Law, were it not that it ſeems better to become ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans Pen than mine. There are yet alive many men that are forward for works of Charity.</p>
                  <p>Obj. <hi>Some ſay, What ſhall I do for hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thou hadſt Faith as a grain of Muſtard-Seed, thou wouldſt ſay to this Mountain of Diſtruſt, be thou removed and caſt into the Sea, and it would be done: Can you truſt God for things eternal, and not for things mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary?<note place="margin">Luk. 16.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Make you friends with the Mammon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi> Riches are unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly gotten by ſome, unrighteouſly ſpent by others, but unrighteouſly kept by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more. Many get that honeſtly, which they do not honeſtly keep. It is by Gods Law another mans right: I ſay to the Covetous, as Chriſt to that man, <hi>Stretch forth thy withered hand.</hi> We read of them, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. <hi>That invent inſtruments of Muſick, drink wine in Boles, and are not grieved for the Afflictions of Joſeph:</hi> Let ſuch yet ſay as <hi>David,</hi> when the Lord gave him reſt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.1, 2. <hi>When he ſat in his houſe, he ſaid to Nathan the Propet, I dwell in a houſe of Cedar, but the Ark
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151471:47"/>of God dwelleth within Curtains.</hi> So I am at eaſe, but many Saints in trouble. Love to the Ungodly is alſo evidenced in mourning for their Sins, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. would there were more <hi>Lots!</hi> whoſe Righteous Souls, in hearing, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are vexed from day to day, for the Sins of the Wicked. It is not, how many tears there are in the eyes; but how much ſorrow there is in the heart: Let your heart bleed becauſe of them who are going merrily to the place of Lamentation, Miſery and Wo; Like men that ſhould go on ſinging, and dancing, and calling for their Cups and Muſick, to the place of Execution.</p>
                  <p>I have ſpoken of ſeveral Duties, of reading Scripture, Prayer, Charity, but we muſt remember all muſt be done in Sincerity, and this is the next thing we ſhall conſider.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151471:48"/>
               <head>CHAP VIII. <hi>Of Sincerity.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>MAny there are, I doubt not, whoſe Sincerity no man queſtions, that will be found formal another day; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that few thought well of will be ſaved. Snow covers Dunghils; Gilt makes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wood and Stones look like Gold: So doth a Profeſſion, and ſome attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, make many Unconverted Men look like true Chriſtians. When <hi>Judas</hi> went up and down Preaching the Goſpel, if any one had ſaid to him, <hi>Judas, thou art now perſwading the world to cloſe with Chriſt, within a little time thou thy ſelf wilt betray this Chriſt to death for thirty pieces of Silver;</hi> would he have believed it? or would he not rather have ſaid as <hi>Hazael</hi> to <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 8.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Am I a Dog that I ſhould do this thing?</hi> Many famous Miniſters, great Preachers, men of great Parts and Zeal, much followed by all, and accounted Angels from Heaven, I fear will in a little time,<note place="margin">Mat. 258.</note> cry, <hi>Our Lamps are
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151471:48"/>gone out!</hi> Many forward hearers, that have done many things, ſet on Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and minded reading, and praying in their Families, will I fear, in a little time, be found to be <hi>Cakes half baked:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoſ. 7.8.</note> On the other hand, there are many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People, that are taken but little notice of for Religion, that I hope will be ſaved. Their Heavenly Father ſees that in ſecret (hearts broken for Sin, and breathing after Chriſt) for which he will reward them openly. Many that deceive themſelves thus plead,</p>
                  <p>I can remember the time when, the place where, the Miniſter by whom, I was Converted: 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.27, 28.29. <hi>When Ahab heard theſe words, he rent his cloaths, he faſted,</hi> &amp;c. God takes notice of it to the Prophet, <hi>Seeſt thou not how Ahab humbleth himſelf before me?</hi> Then <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> remembred the time when, the place where, the Prophet by whom he was terrifyed, ſo as to pray, faſt, and had a Promiſe from God on the doing this work. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. <hi>Simon himſelf believed, and was Baptized;</hi> Verſe 21. <hi>And yet his heart was not right in the ſight of God. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> Doctrine and Miracles Converted ſeemingly him that had deceived many: <hi>Simon</hi> might ſay, I remember the time
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151471:49"/>when, the place where, the Miniſter by whom I was convinced and awakened; and yet he was <hi>in the gall of Sin, and the bond of Iniquity,</hi> Gal. 4.14, 15, 16. Once again, many of them received <hi>Paul</hi> as an <hi>Angel of God, even as Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> (high words) were <hi>ready to have plucked out their eyes, and have given them to him;</hi> and yet at laſt they accounted him their Enemy, becauſe he told them the truth: No doubt many of them were but formal, to whom he ſaid, <hi>Where is then the Bleſſedneſs you ſpake of?</hi> Theſe men could remember the time when, the place where, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by wom they were reformed. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch men can ſay but little elſe, but their firſt Convictions, and Terrours.</p>
                  <p>Others plead, That God hath heard and wonderfully anſwer'd their Prayers: and that they are aſſured from the Scriptures of Truth,<note place="margin">John 19.31.</note> 
                     <hi>That God heareth not Sinners, but if any man be a Worſhpper of God, him he heareth:</hi> And they will tell you of Extraordinary Providences, that they have met with, as an anſwer to Prayer. I anſwer, It may be God heard not your Prayers, but your Murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. <hi>The Quails came at the peoples requeſt;</hi> here was a Providence, but what was the cloſe of all? Some have
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151471:49"/>deſired Children, Riches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs theſe things have made them love and ſerve God, they never were given in a way of Mercy, but Judgment: Or it may be, God heard only the Cry of nature in you, as he hears the cries of Young Lions and Ravens: <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.17, 19, 20. God heard <hi>Hagar's</hi> and <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> Cry; When <hi>Hagar</hi> lift up her voice, and wept, an Angel calls to her, and tells her God had heard the Cry of the Lad, and it is ſaid, verſ. 21. <hi>God was with the Lad. Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> might they ſay, God hath heard, and wonderfully anſwered our Prayers, and God heareth not Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: And yet both were caſt out. I doubt not but God doth work Wonders, or Miracles for their Preſervation, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, that ſhall never be ſaved. Some plead. But I find I have Repentance, I have Faith, I yield Obedience to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>&amp;c. Amen;</hi> would to God it may appear to be ſo! Yet hear the Word of the Lord,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.12.</note> 
                     <hi>The Children of the Kingdom ſhall be caſt out.</hi> Conclude on it, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Art, that doth more reſemble a thing in nature, than Legal Repentance reſembles Evangelical; Temporary Faith Saving; Partial Obedience, Univerſal; Never was there the picture, or <hi>Statua</hi> of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151471:50"/>a man, that did more reſemble a living man, than common Grace doth Saving: Never was any Braſs Half-Crown more like one of good Silver, than the life of a Hypocrite may the life of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Have you ſo repented of Sin, as to loath Sin as Sin, for its malignity, and evil nature? Hath your faith made you to eſteem of Chriſt, his Ordinances and People, more than of all Treaſures? Your Obedience unfeigned, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves? In the account we have of the ſickneſs, and death of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> done by <hi>C.E.</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> one paſſage he hath, to make him famous to the world, (which makes me more to hate the name, and memory of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> than any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of him,) That when his Confeſſor came to him, <hi>Such,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of the man, that he could hardly tell what to confeſs;</hi> inſomuch that his Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father was in ſome perplexity, want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter of Abſolution, till by recourſe to his life paſt, he found ſome ſmall defects of which he abſolved him. The Author cryes, <hi>O Zealous Mind! O Noble Biſhop!</hi> (but let the Chriſtian, poor in ſpirit, that complains with <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7. of a <hi>Body of Sin and Death,</hi> cry, O ſtupid Soul! O vile Hypocrite!) <hi>how ſecure was thy
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151471:50"/>Conſcience, that at thy death hadſt no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but the exchanging of one good work for another, and that when commanded to it!</hi> That was his leaving the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Capua,</hi> for better preſerment. What is related of him, his lying on his bed with his eyes and hands lift up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; his falling proſtrate on the ground to receive the Sacrament; his beſtowing ſo much to feed the poor; all theſe things ſignifie nothing, when the heart is ſo proud, ſo inſenſible of its own Gailt. Then every man muſt try himſelf: The Famous Divines in the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> gave theſe Marks of Sincerity,<note place="margin">Dordrehti Synodus.</note> 
                     <hi>Vera in Chriſtum fides, filialis Dei timor, dolor de peccatis ſecundum Deum, ſitis &amp; eſuries juſtitiae:</hi> A True Faith in Chriſt, (when a man humbly relies upon him for Life and Salvation) A filial Fear of God, (when we fear his diſpleaſure, as well as his Judgments) a ſorrow for Sin ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God, (when we hate Sin, ſo as to fly from it to God) a Hungring and Thirſting after Righteouſneſs (a deſire of Grace more than any thing on earth.)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Conclude on the abſolute neceſſity of Sincerity, and beg the Prayers of Gods
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151471:51"/>Sincere ones: Say then to your Souls, we muſt be upright. If it were proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Heaven, that but one man in a Town, or City, ſhould be ſaved; every man had reaſon to give all diligence, that he might be the man, knowing he cannot dwell with Eternal Burnings. Are your doubts many? beg the Prayers of the Faithful, do as God commanded <hi>Jobs</hi> Friends, <hi>Go to my Servant Job, and he ſhall pray for you, and him will I accept,</hi> Job. 42.8. Go to ſuch a Miniſter ſuch a Chriſtian, be not aſhamed to go to them, to knock at their doors, to ſpeak with them, and enquire,<note place="margin">Acts 16 30.</note> 
                     <hi>What muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> Cry as they in the Viſion to <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 16.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Come over into Macedonia, and help us.</hi> If a man be diſtempered, or wounded in his body, away he goes to the Phyſician, or Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon: Be as careful of your Souls, as you are of your Bodies. If there be any good deſires, cheriſh them: <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. <hi>The Fig-tree putteth forth her Green Figs, and the Vines with the tender Grapes give a good Smell. Ariſe my Love, my Fair One, and come away.</hi> Thy ſincere, though weak deſires and breathings of Soul, are pleaſant to God, and promiſe well. Can any Babes in Chriſt ſay, as the poor <hi>Indian</hi> when firſt awakened, being asked what
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151471:51"/>Sin was, <hi>Oh,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>it is the continual Sickneſs of my Heart?</hi> It argues they are alive to God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Do not too ſoon ſhake off all fears, and doubts. Some come and tell Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, how they cannot ſleep ſome nights, being terrified about Sin, and wrath: I am ready to tell them, where they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake one night, I would they did many: They that have been ſo before them, have no reaſon to wiſh they had ſlept the mean while.</p>
                  <p>Wounds muſt ſmart much before they can be cured. Many break their ſleep by night about loſs of Children, of Goods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and make no great matter of it. You may in a little time, ſay of your hearts, as <hi>Jacob</hi> of that place,<note place="margin">Gen 28.16</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord was here, and I knew it not.</hi> The firſt cry of the New Creature pleaſeth God, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth the Devil. If you are full of fears now, the comforts of God will be ſweeter to you when they come. If you on a Journey were benighted on a Down, darkneſs comes, Rain pours down, one Clap of Thunder and Flaſh of Lightning followed another, and you were wet to the skin, affrighted, and every hour ſeems as long as ten, and in the morning, when
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151471:52"/>light appeared, and the Sun began to ſhine, and you were brought into your Inne, and had the comfort of a good Fire, warm cloaths, good proviſion, and a good bed; would you not be the more ſenſible of the ſweetneſs of theſe things, becauſe of your nights miſery? O Chriſtian, <hi>Sorrow may continue for a night,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 30. Iſa 50.10.</note> 
                     <hi>but joy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the morning.</hi> Are you in <hi>darkneſs, and ſo ſee no light?</hi> Hear you the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings of the Law? See you the Flaſhes of Gods Judgment? Do the Terrours of God fall upon your Soul? When God ſhines upon you, then his Promiſes and Comforts will be ſweet to your Souls.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Never ſtick at any attainments, but be alwayes going on. Are you weak? The ſtrongeſt in Chriſt were once ſo. One hath a good meditation upon this, <hi>The greatest Giant was once a Babe in the Cradle; The greateſt Oak was once a Twig; And the greateſt Scholar, was once in his Horn-book, learning letters:</hi> So ſaith he, the greateſt Chriſtian, was once a Babe in Chriſt, and weak in grace. All muſt grow; ſad it is for any to ſay, if I have ſo much Grace as will bring me to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, I am content: But who is content with juſt ſo much meat as will kill hunger, and ſave life? Or with juſt ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151471:52"/>as will keep him from debts, and ſo from Goal? Strive more and more againſt Sin: Get greater power over Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sins, Company Sins, and the Sins of your Callings. If any ſhould ſay, our hearts are ſtill bad after praying, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtriving, remember ſtill to go on. If a man went to cut down an Oak, the firſt blow with the Ax tends to the fall of the tree, as well as the laſt; if one ſhould ſee one blow given, and another, and an hundred, and the Oak ſeems as firm as ever, and ſhould ſay, it is but in vain to ſtrike any more, what weakneſs were he guilty of? At laſt down falls the Tree: So the firſt acts of Repentance, Faith, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, tend to the pulling down of Sin, as really as the laſt. How many are prone to Pride, Covetouſneſs, unchaſt deſires, revenge, have found this to be true? they have prayed many years, and Faſted, and ſtriven againſt Sin, and yet found (as they thought) but a little change, and at laſt down hath fallen the Sin: And God hath made them very humble, very mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed, very chaſt, very patient. Then take up the Ax, ſtrike, ſtrike, and ſpare not Sin; Sin ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If you find you are Sincere, give God the glory through Jeſus Chriſt. When
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151471:53"/>King <hi>Solomon</hi> was Crowned, what rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing was there! 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.40. <hi>They piped w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h Pipes, and rejoyeed with great joy, ſo that the earth rent with the ſound of them:</hi> Cant. 3.11. <hi>Go forth ye Daughters of Zion, and ſee King Solomon with the Crown where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his Mother Crowned him in the day of his Eſpouſaels, and in the day of the gladneſs of his heart.</hi> God that hath ſanctifyed you, hath Crowned you with a better Crown, of Grace, and will with a Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Angels rejoyced at your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and therefore you ſhould rejoyce: God in heaven, and thoſe your friends there are glad for you, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.32 and you ſhould be glad for your ſelves. You once were under the ſame Condemnation with the wicked. God ſometimes pardons Sinners of the greateſt ſort, and pardons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot ſome of the leſſer ſort: As if a King ſeeing two men, whom the Law had Condemned, the one for Murthering his Child, and contriving to Murther him; another onely for ſtealing of a few Cattel, or a ſumm of Money, he pardons the Traytor, and lets the Thief go to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution: <hi>Even ſo Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 11 26</note> 
                     <hi>for ſo it ſeems good in thy Sight. Paul</hi> runs up all to the <hi>Will of God,</hi> Rom. 9.23. Yet, ſays <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tamen ingerin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us commentum ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutae
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151471:53"/>potentiae:</hi> He is not pleaſed with ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely, <hi>That God is a Law to himſelf: It is Gods Will,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that is true, but why God wills, is not for us to know; why he would wrap up ſo many men in Adam, and they all fell by his Sin; Why Beaſts be not men; or why I was not Chriſts Humane Nature,</hi> is not for us to ask: ſo he.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> You that were <hi>choſen, that you might be holy,</hi> not becauſe he foreſaw you would be holy, ſo you were choſen to <hi>Grace,</hi> as well as to <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Bleſſed are the eyes that ſee the things that you ſee. <hi>You are kept by the mighty power of God, through Faith unto Salvation.</hi> No man ſhall be able to pluck you out of Chriſts hand. If any ſay then, let the Sincere do what they will, they cannot be damned. Though they ſhall not be damned, yet they may be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely ſcourged. God can take away their peace of Conſcience, deprive them of much Communion with himſelf, croſs them in their enjoyments, and make them to go weeping to their Graves. If any reading our Statute-Law ſay, The break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch a Law is only the loſs of my liberty, not of my life; or of my hand, not of my head; and therefore I fear not Law, every one would deride him;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.18</note> 
                     <hi>Grow in Grace,</hi> is Gods Command to them
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151471:54"/>that have Grace; and they do ſo, though the change at firſt be more ſenſible: Let a white cloath be died black, the firſt dip makes a ſenſible, wonderful change, dip it again it is more black, but the change not ſo ſenſible as before: So it is with the firſt and after acts of Grace, firſt and after Duties.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Let us learn more, to enquire into the ſtate and condition of our own Souls, and leſs into the ſtate and condition of other mens Souls. I may know my ſelf, but not ſo eaſily another man; ſome great Profeſſors prove vile, ſome weak ones ſerious, that Dr. <hi>Sibs</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Bucer</hi> after long experience of this, ſaid, he would not exclude from the Lords Supper that man that had <hi>Aliquid Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> any thing of Chriſt. I have heard of that holy man of God, Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> that he once ſaid to his Congregation (who were not pleaſed with it) That if any <hi>Indian,</hi> or other ſhould ſtep forth, and ſay, <hi>I love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity and truth;</hi> and ſhould teſtifie his willingneſs to walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Goſpel, though his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects were great, for Ignorance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that he would admit him to the Lords Table. We all are of the mind of the Church
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151471:54"/>of <hi>England,</hi> that no ſcandalous perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be admitted (and therefore, by the way, many Miniſters are <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> to their own Canons and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) I would admit any man, that by converſe with him, I had reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be ſincere; though I had great fears to the contrary. Whilſt I am writing of this bleſſed Ordinance, this binding Ordinance, this Ordinance God ſo much bleſſeth for the carrying on a work of Grace; Remember we there receive the <hi>Body of Chriſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26</note> The Elements though not changed in nature, yet are changed in uſe: As Wax in Writings, of great uſe, differs from common Wax. One thus expreſſeth himſelf: <q rend="margQuotes">A Prince ſends an Ambaſſadour, and offers a Woman his Son, and gives the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, or Picture of him? the young Prince in Perſon, not the bare Effigies of him is now given: In Perſon, how? Not in preſent, perſonal, phyſical poſſeſſion; but in the true right of Relation, as a Husband.</q> So is Chriſt given, how? Not by any tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but as a Saviour. In this Ordinance God reviveth the decaying Graces of his People, and gives them more ſtrength. It is with our Souls, as with our Bodies,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151471:55"/>they are ſometimes ſick, and out of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: As ſometimes when the body is ſick, the eyes cannot ſee well, nor the mouth taſte well, nor the hands work well, nor the feet go well; by Phyſick, Cordials, or ſome means we are revived, and all is well. Some temptations, corruptions, cares of the world, bring our Souls out of order, that the Eye of Faith waxeth dim, the hands of good Works grow weak, and hang down, the feet of affections are feeble: But Gods Ordinances, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially this of the Sacrament revives us, and ſets us right again. Sincerity then is the chief thing, and above all gettings we ſhould get it, the Price of it is above Gold, above all Treaſures: He that gets it not, gets nothing in the world worth the having. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Fearing God, keeping his Commandements</hi> (which is the ſame with being ſincere) is the <hi>whole of man,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.13. for he had proved all other things to be Vanities: But of that in the next Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151471:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Vanity of the World.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>ALL things are Vanity. All our Enjoyments paſs away like our dreams: We ſometimes have really eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, drunken, and diverted our ſelves with our Friends, which time we deſired before it came, delighted in it when it came: We have ſometimes dreamt we have eaten, drunken, and diverted our ſelves with our Friend, and we had then pleaſure in our imaginations: What dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there now in reſpect of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light between the uſing theſe things, and the dreaming of them? <hi>So omon</hi> ſaith it often in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> that <hi>all things are vanity:</hi> but who thinks of it! O Death, when thou whiſpereſt this truth in the ear of a vain, ungodly man, thou wilt make him to tremble, though the often hearing of it now, will not make him thoughtfull. Whatever in matters of Religion, men may deny, this they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny. Take the <hi>Goliahs</hi> of their
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151471:56"/>Camp, the Giants in all Acts of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they cannot gainſay this; ſuch a place as this cuts to the heart, <hi>Job</hi> 14.20. <hi>Thou prevaileſt for ever againſt him, and he paſſeth; thou changeſt his countenance, and ſendeſt him away.</hi> All the poor ſhift is, that they will put theſe things out of their Minds: Oh but they cannot put them out of the Bible: Here we are but for a moment, and we are all haſtening to a place, where we ſhall be for ever. O Eternity! thou that haſt made ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtout hearts to quake and tremble, let all men ever remember thee. When we were Children, we thought we ſhould never forget the Servants that we loved, the delights that we took up with, and now all is nothing to us: within a little time, all our preſent enjoyments, will ſignifie no more to us, than thoſe do now. Above five thouſand years were gone in the world, before ever we were ſeen or thought of, and here we look about the world, and are gone out of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Call to mind, how uncertain the things of the world have been, to many of our fellow-Creatures before us.<note place="margin">Exod. 14.2</note> 
                     <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was drowned in the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151471:56"/>Red Sea:<note place="margin">Dan. 4.33.</note> 
                     <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> was made as a Beaſt in the field, for ſeven year:<note place="margin">Acts 12.2.</note> 
                     <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> that glittered in his Royal Robes, was eaten of Worms: <hi>Antonius Helioga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balus</hi> Emperour of the <hi>Romans,</hi> his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were very coſtly, and yet he would never wear one Garment twice, his Shoes were embelliſhed with Pearls and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds; his way was ſtrewed with Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Gold and Silver; his Veſſels of ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort were all of Gold, his Rings and Jewels would he never uſe but once: Who, among the voluptuous ſort of men, would not be <hi>Antonius Heliogabalus</hi> now? yet this man had always about him a ſilver Cord, or golden Knife to diſpatch himſelf if he ſaw occaſion; but he did not eſcape ſo, the <hi>Romans</hi> took Him and his Mother (after he had reigned four years) and dragg'd them thorough the ſtreets of <hi>Rome,</hi> and broke their arms, and threw them into <hi>Tiber,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Speeds Chron.</note> that they might not be buried, or the Air be infected by them: Who would be <hi>Antonius Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabalus</hi> now? How have many flouriſhing Nations, as well as men, been brought to nought?<note place="margin">Heylins Coſmog.</note> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> in ſeventeen years deſtroyed ſix Millions of men, roaſted ſome, pluckt out their eyes, cut off ſome mens arms and threw them to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151471:57"/>by Wild Beaſts. This is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in that dream of <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 4.11, 13, 15. Of a tree that <hi>grew, and was ſtrong, the heighth of it reached unto Heaven, and the ſight thereof to the ends of the Earth.</hi> He that came down from Heaven cryed with a loud voice, ſaying, <hi>Hew down the Tree, and cut off his branches, ſhake off his leaves, and ſcatter his Fruit:</hi>—What is become of the houſe that <hi>Solomon</hi> built for <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Daughter? Where are the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Structures we have read of, or the men that dwelt in them?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Conclude on it, the things of the World are but vain, elſe Chriſt, and many good men had never had ſo few of them, and ſo many of the worſt of men, had never had ſuch an abundance of them.<note place="margin">Mat. 17.27 Mat. 27.29</note> Chriſt was ſo poor he could not <hi>pay tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,</hi> &amp;c. had a Crown of Thorns on his head, when <hi>Tiberius</hi> that Idolatrous <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> had a Crown of Gold on his. It is a Priviledge the Saints ſhall have for ever in Heaven, that they ſhall never ſee, nor uſe any of theſe toyes there. The vileſt of men for Blaſphemy, Intemperance, Uncleanneſs, Oppreſſion, they have much of the world, when thouſands that breath after God, and love him above all, have Poverty and contempt: God would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151471:57"/>deny theſe things (if they were not Vanities) to the righteous, and give them to the wicked.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Make the thoughts of a time of <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> familiar to you. Think, Muſt I dye! then Lord it is high time for me, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to live; which no man doth, till he be dead to the world. If you had been made when <hi>Adam</hi> was, and had from that time to this, lived in all the delights of the Sons of men, and were now to die, you would be convinced, that all paſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments were vanity. If you knew for certain where your Graves ſhould be, where your Bodies ſhould lie till the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, would you not (if you could) go often to that Grave, and weep there? But that Curſe ſeems to come on moſt men, that came on the King of <hi>Babylon, Dan.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Let his heart be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from mans, and let a Beaſts heart be given to him:</hi> Hence it is they delight not in God, but in brutal, beaſtial Pleaſures; and though they know they muſt die, yet prepare not for it. As if a man play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Cards, were told his houſe were on fire, and deſired to haſten away to ſave his Houſe, Goods and Children, ſhould ſay, I will end my Game firſt, and by that time he came all were burnt.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:151471:58"/>
                  <p n="4">4. Let the ſpiritual man, the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Soul, be aſhamed, that theſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities have had ſo much of his time, thoughts and deſires. <hi>Epictetus</hi> directed his followers, when tempted to flattery, today, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; <hi>Art thou a Philoſopher?</hi> So when you are tempted to immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate delight in Vanity, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; <hi>Art thou a Chriſtian?</hi> A Diſciple of Jeſus that was de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to theſe Gai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties? Truſt not you in Men, they are Vanity. When <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>l</hi> was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in cruel Bondage, News comes from the Court, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will let them go: You may imagine how glad they were, and how they did comfort one another; but there comes a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter word, then they are ſad: Then a Promiſe again, and they had the Word of a King for it and then it is revoked again.</p>
                  <p>Truſt not to Men, nor Things; your Treaſures, your Relations are uncertain Comforts. Look oftner to God, leſs to the World; yet am I not calling a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to any unneceſſary ſadneſs: He may and ought to take delight in the things of the World, ſeeing they help him to ſerve his God: Meats, Drinks, Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſerve the Body, the Body ſerves the Soul, the Soul ſerves God; ſo that there
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151471:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>is a high end in common things. It is unbecoming a Child of God to be melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, and caſts a blot on his Profeſſion. The <hi>Turks</hi> indeed account their melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Men their greateſt Saints, and keep them, as ſuch, on a publick Stock: They, as ſuch, (as melancholy) are ſitter for <hi>Turks,</hi> than Chriſtians; yet in all our Mirth and Chearfulneſs we ſhould fear Sin. I know Zeal and Langhter may be converſant about the ſame thing; but (ſaith <hi>Ames, De Conſci.</hi>) <hi>Non ſub eadem ratione; Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lus enim reſpicit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; turpe, riſus autem inexpectatum aliq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter placens abſque conſideratione, vel honeſti vel turpis:</hi> Zeal is converſant about a thing, conſider it as good or evil; but laughter may be occaſioned by ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected thing, that pleaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h a little, without the conſideration of the thing as holy or prophane.</p>
                  <p>Is all vanity? then wicked men need not much rejoyce in their abundance, not the righteous much trouble themſelves for their afflictions. Their ſanctified tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall do them much good; when the unſanctified Proſperity of the wicked, ſhall do them much hurt. But the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Afflictions is the next thing to be conſidered.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:151471:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the Benefit of Afflictions.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>THe brighteſt day, hath an approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Night; and the pleaſant Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, a ſharp Winter. Some of the beſt of men have been taken from their enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and plunged into all manner of miſeries: <hi>Job</hi> is a great inſtance of this; In the Morning he had Children, in the Evening none; in the Morning he was a Rich man, in the Evening a Poor man: He draws his own Picture, as it were, when in proſperity, in the 29. <hi>chapt.</hi> of <hi>Job,</hi> and alſo when in adverſity, in <hi>chap.</hi> 30. of <hi>Job:</hi> See what a great change a little time made upon him; at one time he was as a <hi>King in the Army;</hi> at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time they <hi>had him in deriſion, whoſe Fathers he had diſdain'd to ſet with the Dogs of his Flock.</hi> We ſhould expect and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for the greateſt ſuffering, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Let the Fire, the Croſs, or any of the Devils buffetings come,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ignatius,</hi> (if I miſtake not, to the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151471:59"/>
                     <hi>Smyrneans,</hi> for I have him not by me) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>meat for beaſts;</hi> and yet was ſatisfied. Some have been driven into <hi>Caves and Dens of the Earth:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.38.</note> So were many of the Primitive Chriſtians: What (ſaith one) would keep them warm, was their cloathing; the Ground was their Table, Herbs and Roots their diet, Wild fruits and Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries their dainties; Hunger their ſawce, their Fingers their knives, their Hands their Cups; and the next Well their Wine-celler: but he adds, what they wanted in chear, they had in Grace, their lives being ſpent in Meditation and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Fullers</hi> Church-Hiſtory. Sad indeed was the caſe of Mr. <hi>Glover,</hi> in Queen <hi>Maryes</hi> dayes, he was in a Priſon very cloſe, very cold, and very dark, he had no Form or Stool to ſit on, only a little ſtraw for a Bed; but the worſt was this, that all this while he was much diſquieted in his mind, and under fear of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and ſo continued ſad, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, till he was within view of the ſtake, and then the Comforts of God flowed down upon him. Whatever our troubles be from men, we ſhould carry it ſeriouſly, and then chearfully: We ſhould be as the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Job</hi>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:151471:60"/>41.22. <hi>In his neck remaineth ſtrength, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is turned into joy before him.</hi> The Church were Brick-makers in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> ſtrangers had taken their houſes, and ſore troubles we read of in the <hi>Lamentations.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lam. 5.2. Lam. 5.8.</note> If God make us to be <hi>Servants</hi> to <hi>Servants,</hi> we muſt bear all patiently. But by the way, let us bring our ſelves no lower than God brin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s us, and diſcover courage under the contempt of ſome, that would inſult over us in the time of our Trouble: To ſuch a one did the Poet write, when he ſaid,
<q>
                        <l>Non ego ſic ceidi,<note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>id.</note> quamvis ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>estus ut infra</l>
                        <l>Te quoque ſim, inferius quo nihil eſſe poteſt.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>What if ſuch a day ſhould be, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.14. when the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> ſaid, <hi>My hand hath found as a Neſt the riches of the people: and as one that gathere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h Eggs that are left, have I gathered all the earth, and there was none that moved the wing, that opened the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>outh, or peeped?</hi> When we can no more reſiſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n a Bird can us, when we take Eggs out of the Neſt. Now we have gone from God, it may be, afflictions will bring as home: We read in <hi>Jeremy</hi> 2.24. <hi>The Wild Aſſe in the Wilderneſs ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth up the wind, in her month they ſhall find
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151471:60"/>her;</hi> that is, in the impregnation of her womb, then ſhe is burdened, and ſo ſtay'd: ſo many when troubles come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Look unto Chriſt, and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers before us, with what patience they have born afflictions. How was Chriſt reviled, ſpit on, cruciſied, and yet <hi>as a Lamb before the Shearers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.7.</note> ſo was he! Do they contemn and hate us, whom we have ſhewn great kindneſſes to? conſider how <hi>Moſes</hi> was dealt with by an ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people, though he left the pleaſures of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court for their ſakes, yet ſometimes they were ready to ſtone him:<note place="margin">Exo. 17.4.</note> Though <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffered ſo much for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels ſake, yet ſome in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> ſaid of him, that he <hi>walked after the fleſh,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.2. Becauſe he pleaded the power he had to <hi>forbear working,</hi> to have <hi>carnals</hi> from them, that had <hi>ſpirituals</hi> from him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Therefore ſeeing we have this miniſtry, as we have received mercy we faint not:</hi> Hopes he had of doing ſome Souls good, and that quieted him. The <hi>Pagans</hi> of old were wont to ask,<note place="margin">Tertul. Apol.</note> how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Children the Chriſtians devoured, and who were the Cooks that dreſſed them, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> All which reproach they bore pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151471:61"/>Chriſt was not ſtrict enough in his converſe, for a number of proud <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees;</hi> they accuſed him with Sabbath-breaking, and keeping company with vain men. <hi>Solomons</hi> Counſel muſt take place, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.4. <hi>Anſwer not a fool accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Folly, loſt thou alſo be like unto him;</hi> and though there ſeems to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in the next verſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer a fool according to his Folly, loſt he be wiſe in his own conceit:</hi> Anſwer him not maliciouſly, wrathfully, or uſing ſinful words, as he doth: but anſwer him wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with good and convincing words.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Call to mind the wonderful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences that have attended Gods People in their greateſt afflictions. What did God do for <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he went he knew not whither, and met with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles every where?<note place="margin">Joſephus</note> for <hi>Moſes</hi> when <hi>Thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutis</hi> (for ſo was the Daughter of <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh</hi> call'd) took care of him?<note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. R.</hi> Hiſt.</note> When God drowned <hi>Cheneres</hi> (for ſo was that <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> call'd as ſome ſay;) For the Church in Queen <hi>Eſthers</hi> time, when the day for their deſtruction was appointed? Biſh. <hi>Spotſwood</hi> in his Hiſtory of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſpeaking of that Holy man <hi>Cragge,</hi> the night before he was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> died, which
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151471:61"/>cauſed his getting out of Priſon; having loſt himſelf in a Wood, and wanting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, a Dog came and fawned about him, having a Purſe of money in his mouth, and laid it at <hi>Craggs</hi> feet, and guided him to <hi>Millain,</hi> where a company of <hi>Banditti,</hi> or Robbers ſet upon him; one of them told him that he knew him, and once had his Charity, and to requite that kindneſs, he would now ſecure him out of the hands of that ſort of men.<note place="margin">Lam. 3.27.</note> I will not ſay much of my ſelf, who bore the yoke in my youth, nor of a ſeries of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Providences, that nine years ago I met with, in the day when I had not where to lay my head, which for a year after, I did ſeldom think of with dry eyes: I will add no more of that, becauſe I will offend none. Gods care is ſuch of his own, that he ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.11. <hi>Ask me of things to come, concerning my Sons, and concerning the works of my hands, command you me.</hi> I know ſome would read by way of Interrogation, <hi>Do you command me?</hi> but we will conſider the words, as ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Gods great condeſcenſion; yet it is not to be endured, for any to ſay (as once I heard a Miniſter do) <hi>Lord we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore command thee.</hi> If a King ſay to an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary man, in ſuch a thing you may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151471:62"/>me, he doth not expect the man ſhould reply, Then, Sir, I command you; but that he ſhould thus underſtand him: Your requeſt ſhall as certainly be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as if it had the force of a Command, or as if you had the power of command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me: Let us conſider Gods paſt Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences to us, to take encouragement from them; <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.35. <hi>When I ſent you without Purſe or Scrip, lacked you any thing? and they ſaid, Nothing:</hi> What did God for <hi>Joſeph</hi> in all his troubles? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.18, 19. <hi>Whoſe feet they hurt with fetters, he was laid in Iron, until the time that his word came, till the word of the Lord tryed him: Then the King ſent and made him Lord of his houſe, and Ruler of his ſubſtance.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.21. When the Pillars of the Porch of the Temple were ſet up, the right Pillar was called <hi>Jachin,</hi> (which ſignifieth, <hi>He ſhall eſtabliſh</hi>) and the left Pillar was called <hi>Boaz,</hi> (which ſignifieth, <hi>Strength is in it;</hi>) All this ſhews the care God hath of his Church and People, notwithſtanding all contrivances againſt them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Take a Proſpect of all the happy conſequences of ſanctified Afflictions. 1.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.4, 5.</note> They <hi>work Patience, and Patience Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> &amp;c. They <hi>bring forth the peaceable fruits of righteouſneſs.</hi> 2. They make us
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151471:62"/>look to God for comfort, ſeeing none can be found in Creatures; <hi>Micah</hi> 7.5, 6, 7. <hi>Truſt ye not in a Friend, put not confidence in a Guide: keep the doors of thy mouth from her that lyeth in thy boſom: For the Son diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoureth the Father, the Daughter riſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Mother, the Daughter-in-law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Mother-in-law; a mans enemies are the men of his own houſe.</hi> This was a ſad caſe, but how much good came of it? <hi>Therefore I will look unto the Lord; I will wait for the God of my Salvation:</hi> Truſt not in an Enemy, or a <hi>Stranger,</hi> one would think to be good counſel; yea, but truſt not in a <hi>Friend:</hi> But what if that Friend be an <hi>intimate</hi> one? No, put not confidence in a <hi>guide:</hi> But my <hi>Wife</hi> is my ſecond Self; <hi>ſhut the door of thy lips from her that lyeth in thy boſom:</hi> But if I am a Father, I hope I ſhall have comfort in my <hi>Children</hi> whom I ſo much love, and of whoſe Education I am ſo tender; No, <hi>the Son diſhonoureth the Father;</hi> but ſaith the Mother, <hi>Daughters</hi> are more flexible, and I may have Comfort in them; No, <hi>the Daughter riſeth againſt the Mother;</hi> well, if my <hi>Children</hi> be bad, I hope to pleaſe my ſelf in <hi>Children in Law,</hi> Sons Wives; No, <hi>The Daughter-in-law riſeth againſt the Mother-in-law:</hi> If the caſe be this, then
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151471:63"/>I will (ſay ſome) take comfort in <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> or any one in the houſe that loves <hi>me;</hi> No, there is no Comfort there, <hi>For a mans Enemies are them of his own Houſe:</hi> What follows? <hi>Therefore I will look unto the Lord;</hi> Therefore, wherefore? becauſe he could not comfortably look to any other: Away to Prayer, to Meditation, to Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: When any ſay they can take Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in nothing in their Houſes; No, have you no Bibles there? 3. Afflictions make us call to mind our own faults; do others wrong, abuſe us, have not we done the like to ſome men in time paſt? <hi>Solomon</hi> diſſwades from fretting, if we hear our Servants Curſe us, from this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.21, 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou thy ſelf knoweſt that in time paſt thou haſt curſed others:</hi> I have heard of a man that beat his Father, and drew him by the hair of his head towards the ſtreet, when he came to the Threſhold, <hi>Stay Son,</hi> (ſaid the old man) <hi>drag me no farther, for ſo far I dragged my Father, and here I left him:</hi> I have had the Story from the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of that Town, it being a place where Providence hath often called me. 4. Afflictions make us alſo to deſire Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. A man in a Journey, if the way be bad, if the weather be bad, if his Horſe be bad, and if his Body be out of order,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151471:63"/>he more deſires to be at his Journeys end, than otherwiſe he would do. When the Saints come there, they ſhall have their reward. <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſaith, that when <hi>Caius Caligula</hi> cauſed <hi>Agrippa</hi> to be brought out of Priſon, that was committed there by <hi>Tiberius,</hi> he gave him a Chain of Gold that weighed as much as his Chain of Iron, and preferr'd him: Now the heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the Chain of Iron was, the better for him, the greater was his Chain of Gold. The righteous man will bleſs God for ever, for all his trouble; when the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man ſhall for ever, curſe the time in which he enjoyed Proſperity. 5. Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons put us on Prayer. <hi>David</hi> was a man of great troubles, and therefore much given to Prayer, and God delivered, and his Prayers were turned into Praiſes. If any ſay, I have prayed long, and yet the trouble is not over. Long: How long? Thy Life is not long. How long did the <hi>Jews</hi> pray, and wait for Deliverance from the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity? Even ſeventy years. Continue in Prayer, and you know not how ſoon God may appear.</p>
                  <p>Whilſt I mention Afflictions, let me call on all ſorts of men, to prepare for national Calamities; they may be ſuch as God ſpeaks of, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.34. <hi>So that thou
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151471:64"/>ſhalt be mad for the ſight of thine eyes, which thou ſhalt ſee.</hi> Where then will be the Cups, Cards, Muſick of vain men? I ſpeak to you from God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 10.3.</note> 
                     <hi>How long refuſeſt thou to humble thy ſelf before me?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 6.4.</note> We may cry as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy, Wo unto us! for the day go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away, the ſhadows of the evening are ſtretched out.</hi> The day of peace, the day of the enjoyment of Goſpel Priviledges ſeems to draw to a cloſe, when that judgment may be executed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.25. <hi>Wherefore I gave them Statutes that were not good, and judgments whereby they could not live.</hi> I humbly conceive, he ſpeaketh not of the ceremonial Law that he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, but of Idolatrous Commands from men, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>I lifted up my hand alſo to them in the wilderneſs, that I would ſcatter them among the Heathen,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I gave them ſtatutes that were not good:</hi> not as if God gave them by command, but only by his Providence. If any ſay, if that be the worſt of it, we care not: If Popery prevail, we will never be Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts. Go <hi>Judas,</hi> take thy thirty pieces of Silver; and thy eaſe and treaſures ſhall do thee as much good, as that Money did him, which he purchaſed by betraying his Lord.</p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:151471:64"/>
                  <p>The Wicked, that now receive their good things, ſhall be tormented; and the Righteous that receive their evil things ſhall be comforted.<note place="margin">Luke 16.25.</note> But of this in the next Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Heaven and Hell.</head>
               <div type="meditations">
                  <head>MEDITATIONS.</head>
                  <p>OUT of <hi>many Tribulations</hi> ſhall the Righteous <hi>enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 14.22.</note> Lo, this is the happy condition of every Man that hath minded the Duties we have before conſidered. In Heaven they enjoy a compleating of gracious Principles; there they have what here they groaned for, prayed for, a perfect and uninterrupted Love to God, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Him. The Love the Soul hath now to Chriſt, is ſo powerful, that he may ſay with the Spouſe, <hi>I am ſick of Love;</hi> and yet, that Love, if compared to that in Heaven, is but as a drop of Water to a Fountain: Yet if now you ask the Chriſtian, which he loves moſt, God or the World; his Love is ſo ſtrange,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151471:65"/>that it is ſuch a Queſtion, as if you ſhould ask, Which were better, or which he moſt loved, a piece of Gold, or a clod of Earth: There is alſo in Heaven Converſe with the beſt Company; <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and ſhall ſit down with Abraham, and Iſaac, and Jacob, in the Kingdom of God.</hi> What would we now give for an hours ſight of <hi>Paul, David,</hi> or other Saints in Heaven, or Converſe with them? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, if we have wicked, unkind Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, with whom we now dwell, in a little time we ſhall be with them above. We are now pleaſed not only to ſee a King, but his Lords about him; (here is my Lord ſuch a one, famous for ſuch a thing;) ſo above, there is my Lord <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> by whom God wrought Wonders, my Lord <hi>David,</hi> a Man after God's Heart, my Lord <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Gentiles. Joſeph</hi> when he ſaw his Brother <hi>Benjamin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 45.14</note> fell on his neck, and wept for joy; ſo will they rejoyce in Glory, as Children of the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God, and of the ſame Mother, the Church of Chriſt on Earth. There is alſo the Society of Angels, Creatures of ſuch excellency, that they ſeldom come into the world, and when they
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151471:65"/>do, they are ſoon gone, here being no place worthy to entertain them. There is in Heaven an immediate fruition of the bleſſed God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Then ſhall we ſee him face to face, and know even as we are known:</hi> He ſeems not to ſpeak of the Viſion of the divine Eſſence, for that is every where; but of the knowledge of God, and his glorious attributes. And by the way we muſt conſider, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable Attributes are as really the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided Eſſence of God, as thoſe we call incommunicable; and therefore no Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buto of God can properly or ſtrictly be communicated to any Creature, for they are the Divine Eſſence; and if the Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes were communicated, ſo would the Divine Eſſence be: And therefore the Communication we ſpeak of, is only Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical, no Communication of the Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes themſelves to us; (for they are all infinite, and therefore no Creature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of them) but in reſpect of the Fruit and Effects of thoſe Attributes, God works that in Man which reſembles his Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: So we <hi>ſhall be made like him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 John 3.2.</note> as <hi>John</hi> ſayes;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> and ſo be <hi>Partakers of the Divine Nature,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith. How ſweet is Communion with God now! how much more ſweet will it be then! <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151471:66"/>
                     <hi>Tuipſe Coronatores,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ber. Med.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; Corona; Promiſſor, &amp; Promiſſio; Praemiator, &amp; Praemium.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">O God, Thou art the Crowner, and the Crown it ſelf; the Promiſer, and the Promiſe it ſelf; the Rewarder, and the Reward it ſelf.</q> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>We ſhall be for ever with the Lord.</hi> Well may we comfort one another with theſe words, <hi>Where I am,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 14.3. Joh. 17.21.</note> 
                     <hi>there ſhall you alſo be,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; for we are one with Chriſt, though not <hi>Naturâ,</hi> yet <hi>I acto:</hi> The Husband will have the Wife with him. As we now have Communion with God, and Chriſt, is our Heaven begun, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6. <hi>And hath made us to ſit together in heavenly places, in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Heaven is ſuch a place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. <hi>whoſe builder and maker is God.</hi> The Structure is too glorious to be made by the Saints above, or Angels there; they cannot build their own Dwellings, as Men do on Earth, for the Workmanſhip is too curious for them; no, God doth it: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom contrived the Manſions there, and infinite Power made them. This is the place that God purpoſed to bring his People to from Eternity.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.34 1 Kings 7.8, 9, 10.</note> What was the Houſe that King <hi>Solomon</hi> built for the Daughter of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> when he took her to be his Wife, but as a meer Dunghil in compariſon of this Houſe that God hath
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151471:66"/>made for the Sons and Daughters of Men, whom he hath made his beloved Ones? Then ſhall that be fully accompliſhed, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>The Lord thy God will rejoyce over thee with joy: He will reſt in his Love, he will rejoyce over thee with ſinging.</hi> Courts on Earth have their Troubles with their Pleaſures:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>A.</hi> to his Son.</note> one ſaith that well knew what they were; <hi>That a Court is a place of moſt uncertain Air, full of Damps and Exhalations; then there is over-ſcorching Heat, and ſoon over-caſting of Clouds, by the ſudden riſing and depreſſing of Favourites. Great Men are moſt alterable; every puff of Wind fans them into various ſhapes; they which have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly loved to day, have hated deadly the morrow.</hi> So he. But in Heaven there is no fear of the frowns of God, nor abatement of his Love to Eternity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly ſhall be caſt into Hell.</hi> I ſhall not contend about the place, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in the Air, or whether in the Center of the Earth, or whether beyond the Superficies of it; I content my ſelf with that of <hi>Luther, I am ſatisfied in not knowing where Hell is, whileſt I know that it is:</hi> We had better enquire how to eſcape the place, than where the place is: It is a place of Miſery, where the Ungodly ſhall for ever <hi>bear the Indignation of the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151471:67"/>Lord, againſt whom they have ſinned,</hi> Mat. 25.46. Sin is objectively infinite, as it is committed againſt an infinite God: An infinite Offence calls for an infinite Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: This Puniſhment muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infinite for Nature, or Duration; for Nature it cannot be, no finite Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could then bear it; it muſt be therefore infinite for Duration. God hath given to Man an immortal Soul; this Soul goes out of the World laden with Sin and Guilt; is it not reaſonable, that whileſt Sin remains, Puniſhment ſhould remain? But Sin will remain for ever; for, how ſhould it be gotten out, or taken away? What was the puniſhment of the Veſtal Nuns <hi>in Campo Scelerato,</hi> among the old <hi>Romans?</hi> What is the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition?</hi> What is our <hi>Pane forte &amp; dure,</hi> or Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Men to death? Nothing to this: And yet, were any Man ſure, that after ten or twenty years Pleaſures he ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſuch Miſery, how would he quake at the thoughts of it, in the midſt of his Delights? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. The Ungodly are committed to the rage of the Devil. What becomes of the Lamb, if the Lyon have him? How ſad is it for any Man to be delivered over to the Will of his greateſt Enemy, that had no Pity, no Humanity,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151471:67"/>but ſhould take more delight in torturing, than in eating when hungry? It is not in vain put in, <hi>Depart from me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 25.41</note> — <hi>with the Devil and his Angels:</hi> Now they are but Executioners, God is the Judge. Well might <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>Who knoweth the Power of thy Wrath!</hi> Pſal. 90.11. It is the Wrath of an infinite God, of a ſin-revenging God. Let ſuch as fear not Eternal Burnings conſider, what would an eternal Gout, an eternal Tooth-ache, an eternal Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury be? The Ungodly ſhall cry, and not be heard; cry as they, <hi>Jer.</hi> 47.6, 7. <hi>O thou Sword of the Lord, how long will it be e're thou be quiet? put up thy ſelf into thy Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard, reſt and be ſtill.</hi> But that anſwer ſhall be given? <hi>How can it be quiet, ſince the Lord hath given it a charge to deſtroy?</hi> I have many times thought, when I have read the 48, &amp; 49 <hi>chapters</hi> of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> and the laſt Verſes of both, though dreadful things were threatned to be executed on <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Elam,</hi> yet the Cloſe of all is, <hi>Yet will I bring again the Captivity of Moab, in the latter dayes, ſaith the Lord; but it ſhall be in the latter dayes. I will bring again the Captivity of Elam, ſaith the Lord.</hi> But when Chriſt will condemn the Wicked in the great day, there is not the leaſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Pity after thouſands of Years or
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151471:68"/>Ages. <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Bondage (though long, yet) ended, ſo did the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, but there will be no end of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; <hi>God is not a man that he ſhould repent;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.29.</note> there will be no change of his mind; <hi>If God changeth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Al. <hi>in</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſ. Platon.</note> (ſaith a Platoniſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.) <hi>he muſt be changed of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or ſome other; if of another, he muſt be greater than God, or wiſer, which none can be; if of himſelf, he muſt change either for the better or the worſe, both which would argue imperfection in God, and therefore he ſhall be known for ever to be a God that chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not:</hi> God is now preparing his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Death, though vain men conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it not, but are as Sheep, or Oxen, or other Beaſts of the field, that are grazing or ſporting, when one ſtands by whetting his Inſtruments to ſlay them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p>Prepare for the day of Judgment, and when prepared, pray for it. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of the happineſs of the Saints, as to their body, will be in that day: What think you of the particular Judgment in the time of Death? When <hi>Saul</hi> was told he ſhould dye, (for that is the meaning of the word, <hi>be with me,</hi> that is in the number of the dead; for <hi>Jonathan</hi> was a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151471:68"/>good man,) 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Then Saul fell ſtrait way all along on the earth, and there was no ſtrength in him:</hi> In the ſixth <hi>verſe</hi> we find, <hi>In the day of his trouble God anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him not, neither by Dreams, nor by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim, nor by Prophets:</hi> Neither will God ſpeak comfortably to ungodly men when they die, by Miniſters, nor Scripture, nor Conſcience: If you ask what that <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> was? we read not of it as a thing made by <hi>Moſes</hi> or the People; ſome think it was a precious ſtone in the breaſt of the High-Prieſt, that by the change of its colour, ſhewed what ſucceſs the People ſhould have in War; as by <hi>Thummim</hi> what Offerings were accepted: I know Mr. <hi>Weems</hi> throws in one rub againſt this, <hi>Becauſe,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when the Prieſt put on <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim and Thummim, he asked Counſel at the mouth of the Lord:</hi> He pleads, if there were ſuch a wonderful miraculous change of the colour of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim,</hi> there was no need of asking of God; his Opinion therefore was, when the Prieſt had it on, he was inſpired to anſwer to the queſtion: I will not gainſay the Opinion, only I conceive the objection is of no force, for that change of the colour might be made by, or in Prayer, and calling upon God: <hi>Saul</hi> had no anſwer: the Ungodly ſhall cry in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151471:69"/>a time of Death, and not be heard; and when the day of judgment cometh, that great day, the Conſciences of the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Chriſt, may ſay to them, what once <hi>Zebul</hi> ſaid to <hi>Gaal, Judg.</hi> 9.38. <hi>Where is now thy mouth, wherewith thou ſaidſt, Who is Abimelech, that we ſhould ſerve him?</hi> Where is now thy mouth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou ſaidſt, Who is Chriſt that I ſhould ſerve him? Then will he ſay to ſuch,<note place="margin">Exod. 6.1.</note> what once God ſaid to <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>Pharaoh, Now ſhalt thou ſee what I will do to Pharaoh:</hi> Now ſhall Angels and Saints ſee what God will do to the ungodly; but ſuch as are prepared for that day, may Pray for it;<note place="margin">Aug. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> 
                     <hi>Aſpice Domine Jeſu,</hi> (cries <hi>Anguſtine</hi>) <hi>viduitatis, &amp; orbitatis meaelacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, quas tibi offero donec redeas:</hi> Behold Lord Jeſus the tears of my Widdowhood or fatherleſs condition, which I pour out 'till thou returneſt: Pray for the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, that ſin may be no more, that all the faithful may be gathered in: Pray for the eternal Kingdom.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.12</note> 
                     <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force:</hi> You ſee how poor hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Beggars cry at your doors for an alms, if you do not preſently anſwer them, if you frown on them, they will not be gone. Let us all ſmite our breaſts; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151471:69"/>God, what an infinite diſproportion is there between my deſires, and their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects! how coldly do I Pray for a Heaven!</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Get a Settlement in your Hearts of the truth and certainty of all theſe things. It is reaſonable to believe, that verily <hi>there is a Reward for the Righteous;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 58.11</note> 
                     <hi>verily there is a God that judgeth the earth.</hi> God rewardeth not his People now, God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth not his Enemies now, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will do it hereafter. The worſt of Men have many times the beſt of the World, and the beſt of men the worſt. God hath put breathings and longings of Soul in his own after the full enjoyment of himſelf in Glory, and he puts not thoſe deſires there to torment them, but to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie theſe deſires. Men venture much at Sea in hopes of great gain: Let hopes, even weak hopes in many, put them on diligence in God's Service. <hi>Wherefore,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58.</note> 
                     <hi>my Brethren, be conſtant, unmoveable, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes abounding in the work of the Lord, knowing your labour ſhall not be in vain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Let all the Saints admire and adore our Lord Jeſus, that ſaveth them from Hell, and brings them to Heaven. Mr. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his <hi>Looking unto Jeſus,</hi> ſaith thus; <hi>Suppoſe for an Offence thou wert to be rack'd leiſurably, that thy Bones and Sinews
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151471:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>might be pained thirty or forty years; that ſo much Fleſh ſhould be cut off-one day, ſuch a Bone broken another; and by Art the Fleſh ſhould be reſtored, and the Skin cured again; and all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe years thou be dying, and never dead; and all this while thou ſhouldeſt have no Cloaths, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>od, or Sleep convenient for thee; and when thou thought'ſt there was no hope, a great Prince ſhould come, and deliver thee from all this miſery; and not only ſo, but give thee great Treaſures, and one of the moſt pleaſant Habitations in his Kingdom; how would'ſt thou love that Prince!</hi>— Our Sin had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned us to far greater Miſery, and our Lord Jeſus hath procured for us far great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Mercy. It is well God hath prepared an Eternity to admire this Love in.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Do God that Service here on Earth, that you can never do him in Heaven. I will name a few Particulars, and leave the Amplification to your Meditation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Take thy fill of ſpiritual Mourning for ſhine own and other mens Sins now: Thou canſt not do this when thou comeſt to Heaven; for there is no Sin there.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Bear up patiently under all thy Trials now; thou canſt not do this in Heaven, for there is no trouble there.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Deal liberally with diſtreſſed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans now; thou canſt not do this in Heaven,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151471:70"/>for there is no diſtreſſed Chriſtians there.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Delight in Scripture and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the healing of thy Soul now; thou canſt not do this in Heaven, for there is no unhealed Soul there.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Word to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconverted.</head>
                  <p>Are theſe things ſo? Then may I ſay to you what the Prophet ſaid of <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Kirhareſh,</hi> Iſa. 16.11. <hi>Wherefore my Bowels ſhall ſound as a Harp for Moab, and my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards for Kirhareſh.</hi> When Men ran from God, though God offer'd Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.7. <hi>It repented the Lord that he had made Man, and it grieved him to the heart:</hi> Sin hath made him ſuch a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that God loatheth him, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are often in Anguiſh of Spirit becauſe of him. What aileth the Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Man, that though he knoweth he hath ſinned, and is expoſed to eternal Judgments; yet can eat and drink by day, and ſleep by night, as if all were well? Men condemned to die for Theft, Murder, how ſad do they look! but Sin is of a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening nature: Hence it is that their Hearts feel not the <hi>ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nest Conſiderations</hi> in Religion. Ungodly Men are, as one ſayes,<note place="margin">Whately's N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w-birth.</note> as <hi>little Devils,</hi> and differ from the great Devil, not in Parts of Corruption, but
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151471:71"/>Degrees; as a Child differs from a Man.</p>
                  <p>But O man! thou muſt die, and if it be ſo thou dyeſt before thou art made a new creature, thou art damned for ever. <hi>Hell from beneath is moved for thee, to meet thee at thy coming,</hi> Iſa. 14.9. If there were a Sword, a Piſtol at thy breaſt, how wouldſt thou beg for life, if thou hadſt any hopes of being heard! the Sword of Juſtice is drawn againſt thee, and ready to be ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in thy bowels. Cry, cry aloud to the merciful God for Mercy. How often in the night ſeaſon, is there a ſcrole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eyes of thy paſt iniquities, and of judgments to come; and thou turneſt from one ſide to another, Shall I, ſhall I yet reform! When ſhall it once be? If any ſay, I hope to be ſaved though I obey not the Goſpel: This is to ſay, I hope God will prove falſe of his word: or as if a man call'd to work, and promiſed pay, ſhould ſay, Though I ſport, or ſleep, (but work not) all day long, I doubt not of my wages; and ſhould argue from the goodneſs of the nature of that man that imployed him: If others ſay, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent hereafter; So thou ſhalt; but I fear that <hi>hereafter</hi> will be in Hell for ever, when there is no hope of mercy. The Scripture calleth obſtinate Sinners, <hi>Sons
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151471:71"/>of Belial,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.12. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1. the <hi>Sept.</hi> read in one place <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Peſtilent men,</hi> infectious men; in the other place, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Men yokeleſs,</hi> againſt all Law: And this is the caſe of men, that were once glorious Creatures, when in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their Maker. It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable conſideration to them that are holy,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9. Rev. 21.27.</note> 
                     <hi>That no unclean thing ſhall enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi> Your graceleſs Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall occaſion no ſorrow to them there. When they ſee you in the great day, yet they, nor their God will have any pity upon you. Fathers, whoſe hearts were once ready to break for their ungodly Children, or Husbands for their ungodly Wives; or Brothers for their ungodly Brethren; they will not wiſh in that day, O that I could ſave them from the Wrath of God! They will be contented, and not only ſo, but will rejoyce that Juſtice is executed upon them; that God hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon them in their eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who had none by them by any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation or good works. <hi>Turn you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.11.</note> 
                     <hi>turn you, why will you die?</hi> Mind the duties I have perſwaded to before. Let none complain for want of time, when they know, that many of as much buſineſs as they, can find time to mind God, and their
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151471:72"/>duty in.<note place="margin">Jer. 13.17.</note> 
                     <hi>But if you will not hear, my Soul ſhall mourn in ſecret for your pride.</hi> You that cry in Youth, It is too ſoon to be ſerious, or in Middle-age, It is time enough, will in old age ſay, It is too late. I turn from you, to them that I know will hear me, and with whom my pains are never loſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To the Righteous.</head>
                  <p>Praiſe the Lord all ye his Saints, whom God hath ſanctified, whom God will ſave: You may ſing that Song, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.21. <hi>The Horſe, and his Rider, hath he thrown into the Sea:</hi> So your vile affections and Satan hath God conquer'd for you. Grow in grace, as the Children of God, and as the Brethren of the holy Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. <hi>Epictetus</hi> gives a direction to Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, to conſider when about to do an action; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; What would <hi>Socrates,</hi> or <hi>Zeno</hi> do? So how would <hi>David, Paul</hi> pray, read, or do the works of Religion, if they were by you, and were to do the ſame? If your Brethren in Heaven could ſpeak to you, how would they perſwade you to be zealous in good works, as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the ſame Father, and Heirs of the ſame Kingdom with themſelves? A
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151471:72"/>ſtrange ſight would it be, to ſee a King, with a Crown on his Head, taking in a Dunghill: Sad is it, to ſee the Chriſtian that hath Grace, and ſhall have glory, to be immoderately concerned about the things of this life. I perſwade you to that which tends to make your lives hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py on all accounts, and which I have often ſpoken of; <hi>Piety, Induſtry, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Chearfulneſs. Piety,</hi> be ſerious in Religion, and ſeek for comfortable Perſwaſions of the Love of God: <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry,</hi> be laborious in your Callings: <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs,</hi> do good to the Souls and Bodies of many: <hi>Chearfulneſs,</hi> flee all needleſs ſorrow, adorn the Goſpel of Chriſt, and let your Converſations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite others to receive it. Faults in you are bad indeed: The better the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, the worſe is the rent; the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Cup, the worſe is the crack; the better the man, the worſe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order. For your encouragement to walk with God, hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches:<note place="margin">Rev. 2.7.</note> 
                     <hi>To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh, will I give to eat of the Tree of Life, which is in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 7.16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>They are before the Throne of God, and ſerve him day and night in his Temple: And he that ſitteth on the Throne
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151471:73"/>ſhall dwell among them: They ſhall neither hunger nor thirſt any more; Neither ſhall the Sun light on them, nor any heat; for the Lamb, that is in the midſt of the Throne, ſhall feed them, and ſhall lead them unto the Fountain of living waters; and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 22.1.</note> There is that <hi>pure River of the water of Life, clear as Chryſtal, proceeding out of the throne of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 22.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and of the Lamb. Theſe ſayings are faithful, and true. And the Lord God of the holy Prophets hath ſhewn to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the things which muſt ſhortly be done. Bleſſed are they that do his Commandements,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 22.14</note> 
                     <hi>that they may have right to the Tree of life, and may enter in through the Gates into the City.</hi> I end all with this hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Addreſs unto the Lord, That he would come with all his Train of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and put an end to all our Heats and Contentions about the ſmaller things in Religion, and make us zealous of all good Works, and then bring us to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Even ſo come,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 22.20</note> 
                     <hi>Lord Jeſus; That all the Saints may enjoy thoſe Delights, of which it ſhall never be ſaid, Here is</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
